<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some motives and incentives to the love of God pathetically discours'd of, in a letter to a friend / by the Hon[ora]ble R.B., Esq.</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11688032</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11688032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 15:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some motives and incentives to the love of God pathetically discours'd of, in a letter to a friend / by the Hon[ora]ble R.B., Esq.</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 174 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Robert Boyle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME MOTIVES AND INCENTIVES To the Love of GOD.</p>
            <p>Pathetically diſcours'd of, in A Letter to a Friend.</p>
            <p>BY The Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
               <hi>R. B.</hi> Eſq;.</p>
            <q>Let us conſider one another, to Provoke unto Love.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 10.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Anchor</hi> in the lower walk in the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1659</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE COUNTESSE OF WARWICK.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Deare Siſter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Expect you ſhould ſomewhat wonder, that after having for above Eleven years been carefull, to keep this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter from the Publick View, and that too notwithſtanding the Sollicitation (not to ſay, Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) of divers Illuſtrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and even Your Commands, to
<pb facs="tcp:48185:3"/>Releaſe it from its Confinement; I ſhould now at length give way to its Paſſing Abroad into the World, and its making You a Publick and Solemn Addreſſe. Wherefore judging my ſelf obliged to give You an Account of a Paper, for which You have long been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo Highly, and ſo Obligingly, to Concern Your ſelf; I muſt, to remove Your Wonder, inform You, that I am Reduc'd to this Publication in mine own Defence. For, whilſt I was far from Drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of permitting this Epistle to paſſe out of my Cloſet; it happen'd, that a broken Copy of it did, by I know not what Misfortune for me, fall into the hands of a Neceſſitous
<pb facs="tcp:48185:3"/>Perſon, who would needs perſwade himſelf, that, by Printing it, he might relieve ſome of his preſent Wants; and thereupon proffer'd to ſell the Copy for a ſum of Mony. But my good Fortune leading him to a Stationer, to whom my name was not unknown, he, very civilly, ſent me forthwith notice of the Propoſition that was made him; and after came himſelf to acquaint me, that the Copy, about which he had been treated with, being but One of two or Three that were then abroad, ſome or other of them would, queſtionleſſe, ſoon find the way to the Preſſe. This unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Accident did little leſs Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than Surprize me; for, Beſides
<pb facs="tcp:48185:4"/>that it impos'd on me the neceſſity of a Publication I had ſo long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd; and Beſides that I knew, that Compoſures of a very differing Nature being Expected from me, the appearing of This, inſtead of Them, would make this Unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to many, though it had fewer Imperfections than it has: Beſides theſe things I ſay, my Sight was then, and is still, ſo impair'd, by a diſtemper in my Eyes; and the Hours I could diſpoſe of were ſo prae-ingag'd to Philoſophicall Themes; that I could not promiſe my ſelf ſo much, as to Read it over before its going to the Printer. But conſidering after all this, that the Copy I had by me, was like to prove
<pb facs="tcp:48185:4"/>more Full, and leſſe Faulty, than any of thoſe that ſome endeavourd to obtrude upon the World, I thought it leſſe Inconvenient to venture mine own abroad, than to run the hazard of a Surreptitious Edition of a Diſcourſe, that could ſo ill bear the appearing with any other Blemiſhes, than thoſe it brought with it into the World from my Pen. And therefore, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put it into the hands of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe eminent Abilities, the more Knowing part of the Nation has long and juſtly admir'd, and begg'd their Impartiall Opinion and Caſtigations of it, (giving them entire Liberty, to Alter and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge
<pb facs="tcp:48185:5"/>whatever they diſlik'd;) and finding, by haſtily turning over the Leaves, that their Caſtigations were onely enough to let me ſee, that they had heedfully read it over; and were accompanyed with Encouragements, which care was taken, to keep me from looking upon as meer Complements I let it go to the Preſſe, without ſo much as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once Peruſ'd it, or heard it read over, ſince the Stationer firſt gave me the Advertiſement I told You of: Which I made the leſs ſcruple to do, becauſe a Critick, whoſe Judgment and Piety I much reverence, ſeriouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to perſwade me, that I
<pb facs="tcp:48185:5"/>ought not in Conſcience to decline publiſhing, what be was pleaſed to think proper to Kindle or Cheriſh the Flames of Divine Love, in the Breaſts of the Readers. And my Haſte it ſelf did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Promiſe me theſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, That notwithstanding my Book's not comming forth ſooner, I ſhould not Loſe the Excuſe of <hi>Youth</hi> I had, when it was Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: nay, and That the Faulty paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages which may be met with in it, will perhaps be charged upon thoſe, that ſuffered them to paſſe uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, when they had ſo abſolute a Power to Expunge or Reform them. Theſe, and the like Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
<pb facs="tcp:48185:6"/>having induc'd me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Publication of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter, I needed not Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate long, To whom I ſhould Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe it. For, ſince that Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd <hi>Lindamor,</hi> whom it ſo much Concern'd, has left the World, there is no Perſon in it, to whom this Addreſſe is any thing near ſo due, as unto You, Dear Siſter. It was at that delicious <hi>Leeze,</hi> where You are now the Miſtreſs, that this Letter was wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and it was of You that I borrow'd thoſe hours I ſpent in writing it. 'Twas to You that I ſhow'd it almoſt Sheet by Sheet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſolv'd to ſend it away.
<pb facs="tcp:48185:6"/>'Tis You that can beſt Excuſe the Imperfections of it, as knowing not onely the more Obvious, but the more Private Avocations, and other Diſadvantages, among which it was penn'd. 'Tis You that have ever ſince Sollicited me to divulge it, and have given me the greatest Encouragements to do ſo, not onely by thoſe Sollicitations, which imply'd Your own favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Opinion of it, but by procuring me (by Concealing or Diſguiſing my name) the unſuſpected Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of divers competent Judges. In a word, this Addreſſe belongs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo many Scores to You, that I could not make it any where elſe, without manifeſtly Wronging You.
<pb facs="tcp:48185:7"/>I know, Dear Siſter, that it is Not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuall, to Dedicate Books to ſo near a Relation; and that it Is uſuall in Dedicatory Epiſtles, both to Depreciate what one has Written, and to Extoll the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that one Writes to, eſpecially, if it be one of Your Sex and Quality. But You know too, that I never Swore Allegiance to Cuſtom, and therefore will not, I Suppoſe, Wonder to ſee me as little Sollicitous to Conform to it on This occaſion, as on Others. In an Age, when ſo few Perſons have Merit enough, to keep that from being Flattery, which ſhould be but Praiſe, I am not at all Ambitious, of caſting my ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:48185:7"/>upon the unhappy Neceſſity, of either Flattering, or appearing Rude; when by better chooſing the Objects of my Addreſſes, I can, as Occaſion requires, give Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes without Untruth, or forbear them without Incivility. Nor dare I preſume, that a Lye Ceaſes to be a Fault, by being Put into a Dedicatory Epiſtle; as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently the Hurtfull Beaſts forgot their Pernicious Nature, when brought into the Ark Not to mention, that Books of Devotion have generally the strange and unhappy Fate, of being Leſſe-Welcome to them that Moſt, than to them that Leſſe need them. As for the Diſcourſe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:48185:8"/>You, though my Opinion of it may be gueſſ'd at, by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy to which I have ſo long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd it: Yet becauſe, as in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, to have a good Opinion of the Medicine, and the Doctor; ſo in Books of Devotion, (which are a kind of Phyſick for the Mind) to have one, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, or of the Writer, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines us to look after the Preſcriptions and Advantages their Operations. I ſhall ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Diſparage a Diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſe, which is of a Nature, to aim more at the being Practiſed by the Readers, than the being Pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And ſhall not at all repine to ſee it finde from the Publick
<pb facs="tcp:48185:8"/>as Favourable a Reception, as it has hitherto met with in Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets. And now, Dear Siſter, though I know You will not; yet, I doubt, my other Readers will expect, that this Letter ſhould, according to the Faſhion of other Epistles Dedicatory, be Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Commendations of You, and Complements to You. But, though I can Praiſe You, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Disbelieving my ſelf, or fearing to be Disbelieved by any that knows You; Yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that Our Relation, and Our Friendſhip, would make ſuch a Way of Writing misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming
<pb facs="tcp:48185:9"/>me on all Occaſions; I know, Your Piety and Your Modeſty would, peculiarly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow it upon This, where the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject I am to Entertain You with, is of ſuch a Nature, as would make a Flaunting Addreſſe, but a very Unſuitable Introduction to it. The Nature of my Theme, as well as the Strictneſs of Your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Our Friendſhip, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding me here to Celebrate You, otherwiſe than by letting the World ſee, that I dare even in a Dedicatory Addreſſe, without fear of diſpleaſing You, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to Celebrate You. And if
<pb facs="tcp:48185:9"/>it be demanded, Why then I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain not likewiſe, from Writing You a Dedication? I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That I am unwilling to loſe this Opportunity, of making a Publick Acknowledgment, that as I have the Honour to be Your Brother, and Your Friend; ſo I have the Juſtice, to think it very much my Happineſſe, to be ſo: Eſpecially, ſince You are pleaſed to aſſure me, That my Relation to You, has rather been the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than the Ground, of a Friendſhip, that does (whilſt it enjoynes me to Profeſſe my ſelf, without Complement) Oblige
<pb facs="tcp:48185:10"/>me to be, with all the Sincerity that's Poſſible,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Dear Siſter,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Brother, and moſt faithfull humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, ROBERT BOYLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:10"/>
            <head>Advertiſements to the Reader. <hi>(As they were written ſome years ſince, when ſome Intelligent Perſons were to have a ſight of the following Diſcourſe.)</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O prevent thoſe Scruples which elſe might ariſe in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall of the enſuing Diſcourſe, the Reader of it is requeſted to take notice</p>
            <p n="1">I. That though Ignorance hath been of late ſo much in Faſhion with too many of our Young Nobility, that ſome paſſages of the enſuing Papers may ſeem unfit to have been written to a Young Gentleman, yet the Perſon, they were addreſt to, being both a Traveller, a Linguiſt and a Scholler, it was not improper to diſcourſe with him, at the Rate of ſuppoſing him ſo qualifi'd.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the enſuing Letter was not
<pb facs="tcp:48185:11"/>written ſingle, being but the Laſt of Divers, <hi>wherein</hi> Love in generall was Confeſſed, Juſtified, &amp; Celebrated; <hi>wherein</hi> the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved way of Making Love was Explicated, Defended, and Oppoſed; <hi>wherein</hi> Conſtancy and Inconſtancy in Love were argued For and Againſt; <hi>wherein</hi> Platonick Love was Explicated, Celebrated, and Derided; <hi>wherein</hi> the Cure of Love was Propoſed and Preſecuted; <hi>wherein</hi> (to diſpatch) the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points concerning Love were Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of in a way ſuited to the ſeverall Themes, and to the Humors and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the ſuppoſed Writers. But all the Former papers, (written in Complement to a fair Lady) though very free from the guilt of either Licentiouſneſſe or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, have been by the Author judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too little Serious, either to appear Alone, or to Accompany the enſuing Diſcourſe, wherein he has expreſſed his Own Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as in the Former he but deduced thoſe of Imaginary Perſons.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the following Paper was to have been Attended by Another, wherein the Properties and Duties of <hi>Seraphick Love</hi> were to have been Explicated and inſiſted on, but that the Author, before he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that other, accidentally meeting with a
<pb facs="tcp:48185:11"/>French Book, wherein,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L' Amon. Divin. de</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> du Moulin.</note> though what he had already Diſcourſed of, were not han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, he found much of what he had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſet down, was Anticipated; and the moſt pertinent Conſiderations his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Themes ſuggeſted, were skillfully Diſplayed already. He fear'd it might be Injurious to his Reader, and himſelf, if he ſhould either turn a Tranſcriber of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Notions, or decline the Beſt thoughts belonging to his Theme, that the Leſſe good ones might paſſe without ſuſpition for his Own.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That the enſuing Trifle having been written in Haſte, and by Snatches, amongſt diſtracting Avocations, and far from Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Accommodations, is freely Proſtrated to the Cenſure of Learned and Impartiall Peruſers, eſpecially Divines: who are, by the Author, Requeſted, to believe its Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking Paſſages, and Unwary Expreſſions, (if it contain any ſuch) to have been altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Unintentionall,</hi> and ſuch as they ſhall find it never to be more than One Labour, to make him Diſcern and Retract; he being Reſolved, by God's aſſiſtance, to continue ſtill Obſequious enough, to all Clearer Diſcoveries of Truth, to be able to ſay, <hi>Errare Poſſum, Haereticus eſſe Nolo.</hi> And as he is on his part ſo Reſigned, and ſo willing
<pb facs="tcp:48185:12"/>to be Rectifi'd; ſo he expects this Equity from thoſe, to whoſe Judgments he Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, That, conſidering he intended not to write a Solemn and Regular Treatiſe, but a Private and Familiar Epiſtle, they will paſſe-by ſuch Unaccurateneſſes, as are wont to be Incident to Compoſures of this later Nature. He preſum'd, he might ſometimes make Bold with the Vulgar Laws of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, treating of an Eternity that admits them not. He hopes, that the freedom taken in ſome of his Expreſſions, concerning Love, and the wonted Objects of it, would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd, by its being Exacted by the Deſigne he had upon <hi>Lindamor,</hi> though he had not (which yet he has) otherwiſe Accounted for it.
<note place="margin">In a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of all the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to my Lady <hi>T. J.</hi>
               </note> And as for thoſe common Places, which the Method of our Author's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe allow'd him not to Decline, he hopes, the Reader will Diſcern, by his way of Writing, that he loves to uſe them, not as Travellers, but as Hunters, uſe the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies: For the Traveller, when he once gets into the Road, makes it his buſineſſe to keep in it; whereas the Hunter, if he meets one, lying in his way, is not fond of Staying in it, but Nimbly Croſſes it, or Traverſes ſo much of it, as is requiſite to be Paſt through, in the Purſuit of the Game.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:12"/>
            <head>Another Advertiſement.</head>
            <head>Given by a Friend of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's, to the Philoſophicall READERS.</head>
            <p>IT appears by a Paſſage in the Epiſtle Dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, premis'd to the following Treatiſe, that the Writer of it ignores not, that diverſe Learned men expect from him Compoſures, of a very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Nature from this. And indeed, it has been freely told by Friends, That if he will not Diſappoint, and, perhaps, Diſoblige many Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Men, he muſt alſo publiſh thoſe Experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Eſſay's, and other Phyſiologicall Writings, which he is known to have, lying by him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to Gratifie inſome meaſure their Curioſity, who are ſollicitous to know, what is like to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his Philoſophicall Papers, I ſhall ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to inform them, That though our Author does not conceive himſelf, to have made any En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to the Publick, to Divulge any thing of this Nature; yet, I ſuppoſe, one of the chief things that makes him (yet) confine thoſe Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to his Cloſet, is, That, expecting ſhortly
<pb facs="tcp:48185:13"/>Home, from forrain Travells, a near Relation of his, to Whom moſt of them are Written, as the Enſuing Treatiſe is to <hi>Lindamor;</hi> he thinks, it would be Improper, by Publiſhing of them, before his hopefull Kinſman's Return, to let Promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Readers have an earlier ſight of them, than the Perſon to whom they are Particularly written. And as for ſome of his Eſſay's, the Author has been content to Promiſe ſome eminent Philoſophers, that have ſollicited the Publication of them, That when the Party they are Addreſt to, has Perus'd them, he will give way to their Diſpoſing of thoſe Papers, as They ſhall think fit. And though he has promiſed this, but as to ſome Few of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes; yet thoſe that know, how great a Lover he is of Experiment all Philoſophy, and Ingenious Men, will, I preſume, ſcarce doubt, but that, as far as the Laws of Diſcretion will permit, he will, in due time, communicate to them ſuch other Things, as he ſhall think likely, either to Promote Reall Learning, or to Advantage and Gratifie Thoſe, that are Seriouſly addicted to It.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48185:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SOME</hi> MOTIVES To the Love of GOD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Deareſt Lindamor,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, to learn both by the voice of Fame, and the Information of much more credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Relators, that <hi>Hermione's</hi> cold uſage has cured you of the Feaver, her ſcorching eyes had given you: And that when once you found your ſelf reſerved to ſhew what wonders her eyes were able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, you ſeaſonably reſolved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Inſtance of the power, rather of Reaſon, than of Love; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, did your ſelfe the right to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the vain hopes, your Inſulting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48185:14"/>Miſtriſs cheriſhed to manifeſt in you, That her charms were capable to make your flame perſevere, when her change had made it as well cauſeleſſe as hopeleſſe. I could wiſh indeed for your ſake, that you owed your cure more entirely to your Reaſon, and leſſe to your Reſentment; That the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of your freedome may no wayes blemiſh it. But ſince un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allay'd Satisfactions are joyes too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, to fall to many mens ſhare on earth, I cannot but conclude, that your recovery even on theſe Tearms deſerves, I ſhould Congratulate it? For, the French ſay truly, that <hi>Les plus courtes Folies ſont les meilleures.</hi> And li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty being too high a Bleſſing to be diveſtible of that nature by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; I (that ſeldome deplore him, who by loſing his Miſtreſs recovers Himſelfe) think that <hi>Hermione</hi> has but intentionally, not eventually diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged you; and hath made your flames a better return, by reſtoring you your own heart, than ſhe could have done by exchanging hers for it. But that which not leaſt endeares to me your recovery, is, That I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by perſons, from whom I dare
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48185:14"/>Credit even ſo welcome News, that my endeavours prov'd ſo happy as to be conducive to it, and that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations I ventured to preſent you, did at leaſt ſo farre contribute to your Freedome, as to give you the deſire, and the deſign of regaining it. For I hope, I need not tell you, that I ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome uſe endeavours, whoſe proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſneſſe is more more welcome to me, than thoſe, that aſpire to ſerve <hi>Lindamor.</hi> And though I cannot ever pay you any great Services in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to my vaſtly greater deſires, yet I can ſcarce do you little ones in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the delight reſulting from the having done you any. Nor has the Joy which this ſucceſſe of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes brings me, been ſparingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by my having ventured them with much more deſire, then expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of their proſpering; and leſſe out of any ſtrong hope they would ſucceed, than out of an unwillingneſſe to leave the means, I thought leaſt improbable, uneſſayed: being invited to excite you to greater hopes, than I durſt allow my ſelf for you; by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Generalls, who, whatſoever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtruſtfull thoughts they harbour in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48185:15"/>their breaſts, ſuppoſe, that before the Battell, to make their Souldiers fight ſucceſſefully, 'tis as well conducive as requiſite, by encouraging Orations, to make them think they ſhall do ſo: For, although I endevoured indeed to perſwade you, that Reaſon being born Soveraign of the Paſſions though her Lenitie or ſupineneſs doe ſometimes both occaſion and permit their Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; She is ſeldom ſo diverſted of her native power; but that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe pleaſeth to imploy what ſhe hath left, ſhe is able to reſume, what ſhe hath loſt. And though I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you ſhould believe that to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what your Reſentment had begun, was a taske ſo eaſie, that the Victory was as much in your power, as the Reſolution of attempting it: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, I ſay, I was once half perſwaded, that to undertake the Curing of a Lover was the next weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the being one. And, <hi>Linda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> to deal ingenuouſly with you, your Recovery hath circumſtances in it, that make me very apprehenſive, that you are not yet out of the danger of a Relapſe, and that you have not half ſo abſolutely abandon'd your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48185:15"/>amorous conſtitution of mind, as the former Idol of it. I know that from a perſon, who, for one that hath never yet been hurt by <hi>Cupid,</hi> is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of uſing him ſleightingly and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely enough, you will expect En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to preſerve you from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes by ſuch diſſwaſions from Love, as its Votaries will ſcarce vouchſafe ſo mild a Title to, as that of Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives againſt it. And I ſhall ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledge, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that I have been ſometimes no very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Satyriſt on that Theme; and with a pen, relliſhing of the Liberty I cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in myheart, endeavoured to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſe thoſe Servile ſouls, that being born to Reaſon, ſo far degraded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as to boaſt ſolely on exceſſe of Paſſion; and had ſuch low and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thoughts of faelicity, and miſery, as to expect either, from a Womans uſage: All which I thought I might the freelier do, becauſe having never known the infaelicities of Love, but in the ſufferings of others, I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably ſuppoſe, that my Declamations againſt it, would paſſe for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of my Reaſon, not my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. But, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> though the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48185:16"/>extravagancies of ſome mens folly, have been ſometimes too great, to let me avoid laughing ſomewhat Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically at it; yet I am really too little an enemy to Love, unleſſe exceſſive or miſ-plac'd by indiſtinct and disfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Conſiderations, to repreſent to you the nobleſt Paſſion of the Mind, as its moſt hideous and formidable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
            <p>To love even with ſome paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Perſon you would Marry,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>1</label> is not onely allowable but expedient, being almoſt neceſſary to the duty of fixing your affection, where you have once engaged your faith; For, it hath been obſerv'd, that Love doth ſeldome ſuffer it ſelf to be confin'd by other matches, then thoſe of its owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. And few, but they, that are ſo wife as they ſee cauſe to be in Love before hand with thoſe they Marry; prove ſo honeſt as afterwards to be in Love with none elſe. Since therefore, the Marriage of a wiſe man ſuppoſes at leaſt as high a degree of Love, as he is capable to cheriſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forfeiting that Title; I can ſcarce, diſallow the being moderately in Love without being injurious to Marriage,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48185:16"/>which is a Relation, which though I can with much leſſe Reluctancy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit others, then Contract my ſelf; yet dare I not abſolutely condemne a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Life, as expedient to no man, without which, even Paradiſe and Innocence were not ſufficient to compleat the happineſſe of the firſt man. Thus you ſee, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that I do not promiſcuouſly quarrell with all ſorts of Love, but indeavour onely to poſſeſſe you with this Truth, That as antiently, among the Jewes, there were odoriferous Unguents, which it was neither unuſuall nor unlawfull to anoint themſelves with, or beſtow upon their friends: But there was a certain peculiar Compoſition too, of a pretious Ointment, which God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reſerv'd to be imployed in his owne Service; with that,
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.31, 32.</note> the Perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of their friends was Criminall and Sacrilegious: So there are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated degrees of Love, which 'tis not forbidden to harbour for a friend, a Miſtris, or a Wife: but there is too, a certain peculiar Strain, or, if I may ſo call it, Heroick Temperament of Love, which where ever it is found, makes it belong, as unalienably, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48185:17"/>juſtly, unto GOD. A virtuous Wife may love both her Husband and her owne Relations, and yet be truly ſaid to love him with her whole heart: becauſe there is a certain unrivall'd degree of fondneſſe, and a peculiar ſort of Love, which conſtitutes true Conjugall affection, which ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines to him, and reſerves entirely for him, and would think it Criminall to harbour for any other Perſon. So a Religious ſoul may obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, of Loving God entirely, though ſhe allow her affections other objects; provided, they be kept in a due ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to, and kept from entring into Competition with that Love, which ought to be appropriated to him: and which reſults chiefly from, an either altogether, or almoſt unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeable Elevation, and vaſtneſſe of affection; from an entire reſignement to, and an abſolute dependance on the Lov'd Party; from a reſtleſſe diſquiet upon the leaſt ſenſe or doubt of her diſpleaſure; from a greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in her intereſts, than ones owne; from an expectation of no leſſe, then felicity or wretchedneſſe from her friendſhip or indignation, or at leaſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48185:17"/>a perſwadedneſs that nothing can be a greater happineſſe, then her favour, or deferve the name of happineſſe without it. For, where ever a paſſion has theſe properties or any of them conſpicuous in it; it cannot, but by being conſecrated to God, avoid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming injurious both to Him and to it ſelfe. The very Nobleneſſe of it, entitles him to it: as in ſome King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, (and particularly here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) though Veins of coorſer Metalls may belong to the owner of the Soile they grow in, yet all the Mines of the more perfect Metalls, (as Gold and Silver) are by the Law made Mines Royall, and belong to the King, to whom their value appropriates them. By reflecting upon this peculiar Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Love, you may be pleaſed, <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi> to interpret ſuch indefinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as you may meet with in the following diſcourſe. And this Love, I have taken the freedome to ſtyle <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick Love,</hi> borrowing the name from (if the Romiſh Divines be good Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalls of the Heavenly Hoſt) thoſe nobler Spirits of the Caeleſtiall Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, whoſe Name in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to which it belongs, expreſſes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48185:18"/>them to be of a flaming Nature;
<note place="margin">The Name <hi>Seraphim,</hi> in Hebrew, ſprings from the Root <hi>Saraph,</hi> which ſignifies to burn or flame: Whence, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6. thoſe pernicious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that our Tranſlators Engliſh, <hi>Fiery-Serpents,</hi> are ſtyled in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, <hi>Hannechaſim haſ-ſeraphim.</hi>
               </note> and whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 6.2, 3.</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's Myſterious Viſion, ſufficiently poynts at the divine Object, to which the flames, that warm them, aſpire and tend. And me-thinks, <hi>Linda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> that you ſhould find it no faint In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation to embrace Seraphick Love, that you may have the advantage by making your ſelfe a Rivall to theſe glorious Spirits, to make them your friends, and the honour to be inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in a Service, where you are ſure of ſuch Illuſtrious concurrents. At leaſt if you be of the mind of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Youth (to whoſe ſucceſſefull Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour the Conquer'd world was both Theater and Trophie) who refus'd to runne at the Olympick Games, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were no Monarchs to runne with him. But I fear, <hi>Linda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> I have a little digreſſed ſince I might have told you in fewer words, that it is not my deſign in this paper to declame againſt Love in generall, or make a ſolemne Harangue of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48185:18"/>fickleneſſe of women: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as when young Gallants, (ſuch as you, <hi>Lindamor</hi>) are ſubject to caſt away their Love upon unfitting Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, their diſcreeter friends, ſenſible of the truth of the Italian Comick's obſervation, that
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Onectà contra more</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E troppo frale ſchermo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In giovinetto cuore.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In youthfull hearts bare Vertue's wont to prove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But a weak ſhield againſt the darts of love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Without taking any more than ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary notice of their former fond and ſtragling Paſſion, reclaim them by either matching them, or at leaſt (in order thereunto) engageing their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to perſons, whoſe Beauty or Prerogatives may both legitimate and confine their affections. So I ſhall now endeavour to prevent the future gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of your Love to objects, that cannot deſerve ſo tranſcendent and diſintereſt a one, as I have obſerved yours to have been; by preferring and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48185:19"/>engageing it to the true Object that paſſion was born to, the nobleſt it can aſpire to, and the moſt ſatisfying it can enjoy. Yes, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> as it has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been my not-unproſperous Task, to un-hood your Soul, I ſhall now make it my buſineſs, to ſhow her Game to flye at. I ſee that Love in <hi>Lindamor</hi> is too noble and predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant an affection, to be either eaſie or fit to be deſtroyed. It will therefore be my deſign not to ſuppreſſe your flame, but to addreſſe it. I wiſh'd it withdrawn from <hi>Hermione,</hi> not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate it, but to transfigure it. I would not have a paſſion, which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing, but a due object, to be Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphick Love, like vulgar men, be ſwallow'd up by Death, the common fate: But be enobled by a deſtinie like that of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> who, having ceaſed to converſe with Mortalls, dyed not, but were tranſlated into Heaven.</p>
            <p>What has been ſaid already,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>2</label> hath, it ſeems, ſuffic'd to rectifie your love, by diſabuſing it, and ſhowing you, how unfitly it was plac'd on its former ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Your proficiencie in that, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites me to proceed with you to a new Leſſon, and (mindfull of that true
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48185:19"/>Saying of an Eminent Father, <hi>Nemo aliquem amat, quem non vult eſſe melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi>) to endeavour to exalt your paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by directing and ſetling it, upon an Object, the due Contemplation of whoſe Lovelineſſe may Cure as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly all hurts received from any Mortall Beauty, as antiently the ſight of the Myſterious Serpent on the Pole did cure the hurts,
<note place="margin">Numb. c. 21. v. 8, 9.</note> the fiery Serpents gave. For, ſince to gaze ſtedfaſtly on an outward beauty where all your looking will but diſcover the ſame face, is found ſo effectuall to kindle or to blow the fire of Love (which the Greeks prettily enough expreſſe by their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) how much muſt a due contemplation ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour us of that divine, and, though refulgent, yet ever more and more diſcoverable object; where attention and wonder, ſtill mutually excite and cheriſh each other? Whence the zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſeſt and perfecteſt Lovers of God, are the glorious Angells, of whom our Saviour ſays, that in Heaven,
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>They alwaies behold tha face of his Father which is in Heaven.</hi> And thoſe bleſſed Saints, whoſe imployment and whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe is, in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> expreſt to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48185:20"/>be,
<note place="margin">Rev. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>To follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes.</hi> And thoſe unblemiſht perſons are in that place recorded to have kept themſelves undefiled by mortall Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; to teach us, that the nearer and cleerer Intuition, that Heaven affords them of the glorious object of their paſſion, was, not the Cauſe of it, but the Recompence; and that, whilſt they liv'd exiles here on earth, 'twas ſuch a ſpeculation, as I am recommending <hi>(Lindamor)</hi> to you, wherwith they liv'd, (to borrow the Expreſion uſed of <hi>Moſes) as ſeeeing him who is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> a ſight, whoſe glory made them look on fading Beauties, with as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dazl'd and untroubled eyes, as Eagles can be ſuppos'd to caſt on Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes when they have been newly gazing on the Sun.</p>
            <p>To engage your Love,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> to this ſublimeſt of Objects, I ſhall deſire, that all that I have ſaid to divert your former flames, and all that I may ſay to depreciate and diſcredit thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grading and diſquieting Amours, that are wont to inveagle Mortalls, may be lookt upon as meant rather by way of preparative, then of Motive, aiming but to diſabuſe and rectifie your mind,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48185:20"/>that with compoſ'd and unprepoſſeſſed thoughts you may judge of the Object, I propoſe to you. Which to qualifie you to be but impartiall to, this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod ſeem'd expedient, being but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd upon ſuch a Score, as that, on which the Platoniſts us'd to premiſe certain vertues, which they (ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly enough) call'd Purgative, to diſpoſe and fit the mind for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of ſublimer truths. As Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians to cleer the ſight are wont to purge the head, that the eye freed from all darkning and diſguiſing Tinctures, may the more perfectly diſcern the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects preſented to it. And certainly, the Love I would perſwade, is of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that makes nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to it, then the greateſt unclou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedneſſe of the eye, and the perfecteſt Illuſtration of the object: which is ſuch, that the cleereſt Reaſon is the moſt advantagious light, it can deſire to be ſeen by. You know the ſtory of that witty Wench, who us'd merrily to wiſh her Lovers all good Qualities, but a good Underſtanding; for that, ſaid ſhe, would them make cut of love with me. The Divine object to which I would prefer you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> is ſo far
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48185:21"/>from being obnoxious to a Danger of that Nature, that I need not diſparage any other to enamour you of this. For, the Creator is too full of Excellencies to need to be recommended or ſet off by the Creature's Defects. He was ſoveraignly lovely in himſelf, before they had a being, nor has his giving us that paſſion, called Love, made him the unfitter object for it. To love God but becauſe your Miſtriſs has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall faults, is a greater, then any of thoſe for which you have declin'd her; and is ſuch a Soloeciſm in Seraphick Love, as it were in the Perſian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (for that has yet imbracers in the Eaſt, as thoſe, that have there converſ'd with them, aſſure me) to make the Spots, that blemiſh the Moon, the Motives of their worſhipping the Sun. <hi>Hermione</hi> is a Lady, to whoſe noble Relations I am too much a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, not to have a Reſpect for Her; and I cannot, without concluding her an extraordinary perſon, remember how lately ſhe enjoy'd the honour of Captivating <hi>Lindamor:</hi> and though ſhe has ſince by injuriouſly declining, juſtly forfeited the glorious Title of his Miſtriſs; yet the Qualities, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48185:21"/>gave it her, made me among divers others like her ſo well, that 'tis now my quarrell to her, that ſhe Is not, what ſhe Was. And therefore, what ever may fal from my pen to her diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, relates to her but as ſhe was, or may again be, an Obſtacle to your devotedneſſe to Seraphick Love. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you to which (all this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>Lindamor</hi>) I muſt do you the right to tell you, that God deſerves the higheſt Elevation of your Love, though <hi>Hermione</hi> had not rejected it. Were ſhe not onely as Handſome as you fancyed her, but as Conſtant as you wiſhed her, Her beauty, and her Friendſhip too concurring, could not have made her other, than, as Diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious as Injurious, a Rivall unto God; and, in the very fruition of as obliging returnes, as her Kindneſſe could have made your Paſſion, ſhe would have deſerv'd but a more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Degree of it. Angels, to whom women were never falſe or cruell, love their Maker above all things:
<note place="margin">Rev 22.4. &amp; 19.1.</note> and he to whom St. <hi>John</hi> preſents his ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, refuſed it for himſelf. to direct it unto God. Would not you your ſelf, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> have thought your <hi>Hermione</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48185:22"/>abſolutely handſome, though Moores had not worn the Devill's Livery; and the thing call'd Deformity, had been as much a ſtranger, as it is unwelcome to her ſex. 'Tis true, ſuch is our frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> needed a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and oppreſſive bondage in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to make them reſolve on returning to the bleſt Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> So often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, the amorous Soul needs the harſh uſage of a diſdainfull Miſtriſs, to diſguſt it with its thraldome, and make it aſpire to its more genuine and ſatisfying Object. I may therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Hermione's</hi> Defects to have given you freedome and occaſion, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Prerogatives of Seraphick Love: But I muſt not allow them to be the chief Motives of your imbracing it; For, it were too injurious to its glorious Object, to make that but the Refuge of a Defeated Paſſion, whoſe Tranſcendency entitles it to more than the moſt elevate and entire one. Alas, God needs not theſe beggerly Parallels with any fading objects, to become that of our diſabus'd Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and He were Lovely Without compariſon as well as He is ſo Above it. And though I be not ſo unjuſt, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48185:22"/>to deny, that there are Ladies (ſome of which I have the happineſſe not to be unknown to my ſelfe) whoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies are capable to ennoble their whole Sex: Yet their greateſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments compar'd to his Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe gifts they are, are, in that Eclipſing company, as inconſpicuous as the faint Qualities of more ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary perſons. As, when in a cleer Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the riſing-Sun vouchſafes to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit us, as well thoſe Bright Starrs, that did Adorn our Hemiſphere, as thoſe Dark Shades, that did benight it, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: Conſonantly whereunto, give me leave to obſerve to you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that though divers of God's Attributes are through his goodneſſe participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Creatures, yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes ſo vaſt a diſparity betwixt the excellencies, that it aſcribes to men, and the ſame Perfections conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as they exiſt in God, that it ſeems abſolutely to exclude created Beeings from any Title to thoſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes; becauſe they poſſeſſe them but in a way ſo inferior to that tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, peculiar, and divine manner, in which, they belong to God. Thus our Saviour ſayes to him that (taking
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48185:23"/>him but for a man) call'd him good, <hi>Why callest thou me good?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>There is none good but One</hi> (that is) <hi>God.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> calls God (or Chriſt) the onely Potentate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though the earth be ſhared by ſeverall Potentates; and even the Devout <hi>Evnuch</hi> in the <hi>Acts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.17. Luk. 1.52.</note> and the depoſed Grandees men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Bleſſed Virgin in her Canticle, are, in the Original, ſtyled Potentates.
<note place="margin">Mat 25.5.</note> Thus, though there be wiſe Virgins as well as fooliſh; and though our Saviour tells us,
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.8.</note> That <hi>the Children of this world are in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration wiſer, than the Children of Light:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. 1 Tim. 6.16.</note> Yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſcruples not to rearm his Maker, <hi>The onely wiſe God;</hi> and thus he elſewhere Paraphraſes him, <hi>He that onely hath immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> Though Angels and humane Souls be deathleſs. In ſo incommunicable a manner does the Superiority of God's nature make him poſſeſſe thoſe very Excellencies, which the diffuſiveneſſe of his goodneſſe, makes him pleaſed to communicate. I am the more zealous, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> to transfigure your Love into Devotion (which I muſt deſire you to look upon but as a varied name for <hi>Seraphick Love</hi>) becauſe I have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48185:23"/>obſerv'd your paſſion to have been extreamly impatient of confinement, and to have eſteem'd whatever may be term'd Limits to be Priſons. Few therefore can Need more or Deſerve better, an object for their love, for which too immenſe a vaſtneſſe were impoſſible. And ſuch a one is God; whoſe ſoveraign Perfections render him ſo uncapable of being lov'd Too Much, that the moſt aſpiring paſſion can ſcarce arrive (ſo much, as) to leſſen its diſproportion to the object. Other paſſions like other Rivers, are moſt lik'd, when they calmly flow within their wonted Banks: but of <hi>Seraphick Love,</hi> as of <hi>Nilus,</hi> the very Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might be deſireable, and his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings make him the more welcome. For mortall beauties, our paſſions are like our ſelves: If our Stature chance to exceed a certain ſize or ſtandart, it make us monſtrous: but Devotion is like a flawleſs Diamond, where the bigneſſe taxes the Value and the unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall Bulke both rates and inhances the Luſtre and the Price. To give GOD All our Love is the greateſt command both of the Law and Goſpell (in its capacious &amp; teeming womb both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48185:24"/>and cheriſhing all the other ſervices, God requires) and that there is not more exacted of us, is not, that an addition were Culpable, but becauſe it is Imposſible. So noble is the nature of Devotion, that it admits of failings but by one of the extreams, which is that of Defect. For, Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie (whoſe office 'tis to reſtrain us from approaching the utmoſt Limits,) which in other pasſions is an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is here an imperfection. Or, at leaſt, if Mediocrity be that which cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates pasſions vertues; the Mediocrity of this Love muſt conſiſt in the Exceſſe of it, ſince that is it, which makes it moſt a vertue.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1. <hi>Cervina caro ſicca eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Sennert. <hi>Inſti. De Alimenter facultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> The man after God's own heart is not a fear'd to own even to his Maker an ardency of love for Him, which muſt be expreſt with the ſignificant Metaphor of Thirſt; and that ſuch a Thirſt too, as makes the panting Hart (by Naturalliſts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be a very drie Creature) bray (as I remember the Hebrew hath it) for thoſe refreſhing ſtreams, whoſe want diſtreſſes and reduces her to an almoſt gaſping condition: <hi>My</hi> very <hi>Soul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thirſteth for God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 2.</note> And we know that thirſt is not only ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48185:24"/>violent an appetite, that it leſſens the wonder of that Monarch's Bargain, whom Hiſtory reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds to have parted with his Kingdome for a cup of water: but thirſt doth ſo confine our longings to what it craves, that nothing elſe can ſatisfie them. The wealth of both the Indies would not excuſe the want of a needed Cup, ſuppoſing their Poſſeſſor tormented with an Appetite, which cannot be quench't but by Drink. To which I muſt adde, that the uneaſineſſe of unrelieved Thirſt, is not, like that of other inconveniences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſen'd by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, but grows by laſting the more unſupportable. The ſame inſpired Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſcruples not alſo to profeſſe ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſo active a Concern for Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, that the <hi>zeal of Gods houſe had eaten him up;</hi> and hugely troubled he is, that others are not affected with the ſame zeal.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.158.</note> 
               <hi>I beheld</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the Tranſgreſſours, and was grieved, becauſe they kept not thy Word.</hi> Nay, <hi>Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>run down mine eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem v. 136.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they keep not thy Law;</hi> and to manifeſt, how much the tenderneſſe and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'dneſſe of his Love, made him think thoſe his friends or enemies, that were ſo to God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101.6.</note> 
               <hi>Mine eyes</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſhall be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48185:25"/>upon the faithfull of the Land, that they may dwell with me. He that walketh perfect in the way, he ſhall ſerve me. Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate Thee, and am not I grieved with thoſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>that riſe up againſt Thee? I hate them with a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, I count them mine Enemies.</hi> At this Rate, did pious <hi>David</hi> love his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but he was ſo far from thinking this rate Exceſſive, that, tranſported by the ſenſe of his perſonall diſability, to pay that Divine object all the Love that his perfections merited: he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to rouze up all his owne faculties to praiſe God,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 103.1.</note> 
               <hi>(Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoul, and all that is within me, bleſſe His holy Name,)</hi> but he invites all the Godly to aſſiſt him in the payment of ſo vaſt a debt,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 117.1.</note> 
               <hi>(Love the Lord all ye Saints, for &amp;c.)</hi> And again, <hi>(Praiſe the Lord all ye Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, praiſe him all ye people.)</hi> And not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent neither frequently to do this, as may appear by very many paſſages of his ſacred Poems,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 138.2.</note> he extends his Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Angells, and all the other Hoſts of God, and concludes the book of Pſalms with a, <hi>Let every thing, that hath breath, praiſe the Lord:</hi> Hallelujah. Nor does it invalidate, what has now been delivered.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48185:25"/>
            <p>That ſome men have,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label> even by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Perſons, been blamed for too much Devotion: for, it was not an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Love, but a want of Diſcretion, that was guilty of their faults; The expreſſions of our Love to God, ought to be regulated not by our blind and wild fancies, but by his revealed will, (as Chriſt ſayes, <hi>If you Love me, keep my Commandements</hi>) and therefore it is very poſſible, to be too devout, not becauſe any expreſſion of Seraphick love can be made with too much Ardency, whil'ſt 'tis conſidered abſtractedly in it ſelfe, and irrelatively to the reſt; But becauſe, that there being ſeverall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Love which require an Ardency of it; 'tis injurious, to exerciſe all that in one alone, or a few, that belongs equally to the neglected others. We muſt not, (as too many Profeſſours are now wont to do, of whoſe error you may receive a fuller accompt in ſome other papers,) daſh in pieces the two Tables of the Law againſt one another; But muſt ſo <hi>love GOD with all our hearts,</hi> as <hi>to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelves.</hi> You know, what our Saviour ſaith to the Phariſees,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note> that Tithed Mint and Cummin,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48185:26"/>with a neglect of Judgement, Mercy, and Faith, thoſe weightier matters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Law; <hi>Theſe ought you (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have done, and not to leave the other undone.</hi> And indeed this Partiality, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> which makes us diſplay ſo much of the ſtrength and vigour of our Spirits in ſome few favorite-Duties, that we can but languidly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functorily perform thoſe others, we are leſſe fond of, begets in Devotion a diſeaſe, not unlike that new one in Children, we call the Rickets, which ſome Learned Phyſicians do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably conceive to ariſe from the unequall Nutrition of the parts; for, though none of them receive exceſſive Nouriſhment, yet ſome of them recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as much as is convenient for them, and thereby growing up to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bigneſſe, whilſt others are leſſe nouriſhed, than (were the Body health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) they would be, do grow ſo little, that the ſounder parts ſeem Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown, and ſo the diſproportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Them, and the Ricketting ones makes the whole Body, they compoſe, miſ-ſhapen, and unweildy. But, <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi> this proves not, that we can love God too much, but onely, that we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48185:26"/>may imploy too much of that Love, in this or that way of expreſſing it. Whilſt we are,
<note place="margin">Job. 4.19.</note> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks) Inhabitants of theſe <hi>houſes of Clay,</hi> there are many Duties, which do as well challenge an intenſity of our affections, as thoſe, which relate more immediately to God. As St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.32, 33, 34.</note> That there is difference betwixt married and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Perſons; the affections of the one being at liberty, to devote themſelves more undiſtractedly to God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thoſe of the other are diſtracted, as <hi>Adam</hi>'s were, betwixt his Maker and his Rib. But, where a direct and immediate expreſſion of Love to God, defraudes not any other Duty, there it is free from the danger of exceſſe. Though Prayers may eaſily be too long, and Faſts grow exorbitant; yet Chriſt could ſpend the whole night in Prayer, and faſt forty dayes without immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſſe, when the other expreſsions of his Love to his Father, and the other exerciſes of his Mediatory Function, were not thereby diſturb'd,
<note place="margin">1 King. 19.8.</note> but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and promoted. And ſo <hi>Elijah</hi> might inculpably faſt long, when that faſting did not diſable him to proſecute his journey to the Mount of God; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48185:27"/>though juſt men here on Earth muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their Love to their Maſter, by (that buſie diſtracting, and remoter way of ſervice) Trading with his Talents truſted to them; yet when their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſture of Mortality diſpenſes them from thoſe laborious and avocating du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to diſtreſſed Chriſtians, and their owne ſecular Relations, which were here requiſite to be perform'd; their glorified ſpirits may now, without any immoderate devotion, imploy, I ſay not, their Time, but their Eternity it ſelfe in Converſing with God, and following the Lamb whitherſoever he goes. And congruouſly I obſerve, that the four myſterious Beaſts,
<note place="margin">Rev. 4.6, 7.</note> allow'd to approach neereſt to the Throne of God (though their many wings and more numerous eyes, intimate them of a very active nature) are repreſented to us in the Apocalypſe, as addicted but to one imployment,
<note place="margin">verſ. 8.</note> ceaſing <hi>neither day nor night from ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty;</hi> and from <hi>giving Glory, and Honour, and Thanks unto him.</hi> And of <hi>thoſe that have white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Robes in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> this account is in the ſame book given
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48185:27"/>us,
<note place="margin">Rev. 7.14, 15.</note> that <hi>they are before the Throne of God, and ſerve Him day and night in his Temple.</hi> So true it is, that no degree of Seraphick Love can be Exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, nay nor any expreſsion of it, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate, unleſſe it be made ſo, not by its Greatneſs, but by its Uſurpation, whereby, it either engroſſes or invades what belongs to its injur'd, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing aſſociates. Our Love unto the Creatures is a Preſent, but unto God it is a Tribute: and though we may eaſily play the Prodigalls in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (over-freely) with our Guifts, we can ſcarce be ſo in the payment of our Debts; for, be the Summes never ſo vaſt we pay away, their being due in ſpite of their being great, makes the disburſement too much an Act of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to be one of Profuſeneſſe: <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick Love,</hi> (whoſe Paſſionateneſſe is its beſt Complexion) has then moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach't its nobleſt meaſure, when it can leaſt be meaſured: nor ought its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to admit any other limits, then an utter diſability to exceed thoſe, that terminate it. For he alone loves God, as much as he Ought, that loving Him as much as he Can, ſtrives to repaire the deplored imperfection of that love,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48185:28"/>with an extream Regret to find it no greater. Such a ſublimity of love will beſt intitle you to the Conſolation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing from that memorable paſſage of St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.16.</note> where he ſayes, that <hi>God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi> Which ſupplies me with a forcible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, to invite you to an eager aſpiring to a Tranſcendency in devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince it may render ſelfe-deniall ſo eaſie, that 'twill (at laſt) almoſt deveſt that name. For, this ſublimer love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by an intimate conjunction with its Object, wholly devoted to it, and throughly refined from all baſe droſſe of ſelfiſhneſſe and intereſt, nobly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a moſt ſtrict Union of our wills with God's, or (rather) a perfect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the one to the other. And thus, when it is become your will to obey His, no diſpenſations of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will immoderately diſquiet you; for, you poſſeſſe your wiſhes in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and in Bulke, though poſſibly not alwayes in Retaile; for, your chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deſire being to ſee your Maker's will fulfilled, your knowledge of his being the Soveraign and uncontrolled Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of Events, aſſures you, that all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48185:28"/>that can befall you, are but exact accompliſhments of His Will, and conſequently of yours ſo far forth, as that is included and compriz'd in his. When you have Reſign'd, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſign'd, your expropriated will (if I may ſo call it) to God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, (as it were) entruſted him to will for you; all his diſpoſalls of, and his diſpenſations towards you, are, in effect, the acts of your owne will, with the Advantage of their being directed and ſpecified by Him. An Advantage that does at once aſſure you both of their Rectitude and their Succeſſe. God's Wiſdome, Power, and Love to you conſider'd, how much more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py muſt you be in your Elections of his naming for you, than your immediate owne? The Patient thinks himſelfe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, to gratifie his Phyſitian, for chooſing for him, what ſorts of meat he is to feed on; though the Doctor be wont to make ſuch a choice for him, as deprives him of the Diſhes he beſt likes, and oftentimes confines him to thoſe he loaths. Alas, how often might God ſay of our requeſts, as Chriſt did of thoſe of the two aſpiring Diſciples; <hi>Ye know not what ye ask.</hi> I admire,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48185:29"/>and bluſh to read in a Heathen Satyriſt, ſo Heavenly a Leſſon, as,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Permittes ipſis expendere Numini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quid</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conveniat nobis, rebuſque ſit utile no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nam pro Jucundis utilia quaeque da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt Dî.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charior est illis homo, quàm ſibi: nos animorum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Impulſu, &amp; caecâ pravâque cupidine ducti,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conjugium petimus partumque uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is; at illis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Notum, qui pueri, qualiſque futura ſit uxor.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unto the wiſer gods the care per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,</l>
                     <l>Of what's for us and our affairs moſt fit.</l>
                     <l>They will for Pleaſant things the Beſt confer;</l>
                     <l>To whom Man is, than to himſelf, more dear.</l>
                     <l>We by our blinder paſſions led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray,</l>
                     <l>Do for a Wife perhaps or Children pray:</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48185:29"/>
                     <l>Which they may chance refuſe us out of Love,</l>
                     <l>Knowing, what both the Wife and Boyes would prove.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of which made a heathen Philoſopher ſay, That he was wont onely in generall Termes to beg Good things of the gods, leaving it to them, to determine what things were Good for him: And indeed, our own wiſhes are but too commonly as blind as <hi>Rachel's,</hi> who having ſo eagerly lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Children that ſhe impatiently cryes, <hi>Give me Children, or elſe I dye;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 35.18.</note> dyed in Child-bearing: And as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the wiſhers, as their Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings prov'd to the Murmuring <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.33.</note> who loathing the wholeſome Manna (that bread of Angells) God had provided for them, are their own Bane in the fleſh, they had ſo greedily luſted for. Thus, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affrightning vertue of Selfe-denyall, proves to be little more, than a Son's Letter of Attorney to his Father, of whoſe paternall fondneſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate abilities in the management of affairs, his confidence amounts unto a certainty. Nay, till my ſecond
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48185:30"/>thoughts check'd the over-forward Impetuoſity of my firſt, I was about to adde; Since God reſents an infinite ſatisfaction in the accompliſhment of his own will, your making over your whole will to God, will impart to you that felicity, proportion'd to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the reſignment. And, as the eye whilſt by the Optick Nerve ty'd unto the head, ſo chain'd can taſte delights; which it is dead to, being once ſever'd from it, though (otherwiſe) it enjoy the beſt condition of which its inanimate Nature can be ſuppos'd to be capable: So may your will by an Identity or Sameneſs (in Tendency, though not in Nature) with your Maker's, as twere engrafted into Gods, receive a new, and an enlarg'd capacity, which wil enable you to contain, and relliſh joyes, highly tranſcending thoſe, which the fulleſt fruition of your private wiſhes were able to create. Thus ſelf-deniall is a kind of holy aſſociation with God, and (by making you his partner) intereſſes you in all his happineſſe, and acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And conſonantly we ſee that Glorified Saints and Bleſſed Angells, whoſe wills have the moſt exquiſite and exact conformity to God's, enjoy a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48185:30"/>happineſs moſt appreaching His; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Apoſtate Spirits in a confirm'd Repugnancy to his will, find the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamitie of wretchedneſſe.</p>
            <p>But though I dare not own, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>5</label> ſo bold a Sally, yet I dare without Scruple improve the diſcourſe, that preceded it, to make out to you an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious difference of <hi>Seraphick Love</hi> from Ordinary Flames. For, he that makes a Preſent of his heart to any Mortall Beauty, even by her welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it and lodging it with her own, grows ſubject to have it wounded in her breaſt. Thoſe misfortunes reach him that would otherwiſe terminate in her: hir afflictions torment him, whilſt his own reprieve him; and the Felicity of two perſons grows requiſite to make one happy. The letting out our love to mutable Objects, doth but inlarge our hearts and make them the wider Marks for fortune, and capable of being wounded in more places: For, although Love may as well make us participate the Joyes, as reſent the Infelicities of the Parties lov'd; yet even the leaſt unhappy perſons do in ſo fickle and ſo tempeſtuous a Sea as we all find this world, meet with ſo many
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48185:31"/>more either croſſe winds or ſtormy guſts, then proſperous gales; and we are ſo much more ſenſible of Pain than Pleaſure (an akeing corne, though leſſe then a ſickneſſe, unfitting us to relliſh, the otherwiſe perfect health of the whole body) that even Friendſhip it ſelfe, though a much calmer affection than Love, ought to be declin'd as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to our quiet, did we conſider it, but as a Partnerſhip of Fortunes, not an Exerciſe of Vertues. But he, whoſe wiſer Love ſettles it ſelfe on God, is not onely by the immutable and even Eſſentiall happineſſe of that Adorable Object, ſecur'd from participated infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitys; but finds his perſonall croſſes and diſtreſſes ſweetned by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that what he moſt loves, is moſt happy; and as able as willing in due time to make Him ſo. And though <hi>Seraphick Love</hi> makes us partake but God's Felicities, yet his acceptance of it makes him reſent Our ſorrows: <hi>In all their afflictions he was afflicted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 63.3.</note> ſayes the Prophet of God, and of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi> And ſo the Son of God (who is ſo much one with thoſe that love him, that both he as the Head, and they as the members are ſometimes, as making
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48185:31"/>up one body, call'd by one name,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12.</note> Chriſt) though as high as Heaven above the reach of perſonall or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate perſecutions, calls out to <hi>Saul</hi> for an intention of harming thoſe, that lov'd him: <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> And, to demonſtrate the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of this Compaſſion, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſays to the return'd <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God: <hi>He that toucheth you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>toucheth the apple of his Eye.</hi> Nor is God's compaſſion like a Miſtreſſe's, a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only and an uſeleſs pitty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſuffering Lover is oftentimes leſſe comforted as it proceeds from her kindneſs, than afflicted becauſe it breeds her diſquiet: But God's is a compaſſion, though Active, yet Serene, and worthy of Himſelf, which without produce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſcompoſure, produces the effects of the moſt ſenſible Pitty, by engaging him to a timely Reliefe and Reſcue: As that freſhly-mentioned Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>In all their affliction he was afflicted;</hi> is immediately follow'd by, <hi>And the Angel of his preſence ſaved them; in his love and in his pitty he redeemed them, and he bare them, and carried them all the daies of old.</hi> Yes, this pitty for its not diſturbing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48185:32"/>Gods Happineſſe, enclines him not the leſſe to expreſſe a ſenſe of our Miſeries and makes us find (to uſe a Scripture phraſe as I would render it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Grace for an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune reliefe;</hi> I ſay, with the divine Writer, an Opportune or Seaſonable Relief, becauſe it comes not alwayes when it is moſt deſired, but when it is moſt fit; And when that is, he that hath at once all preſent paſt and future things in his Proſpect, is fitteſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. Chriſt's words to his Diſciples, <hi>(It is not for you to know the Times or the Seaſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>which the Father hath put in his own power,)</hi> are applicable to more caſes, then that, which occaſioned them.
<note place="margin">Mar. 7.27</note> The <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> woman muſt put up a Refuſall, and the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full name of Dog (which yet, by the way, was a Paraphraſe commonly enough us'd by the Jews of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<note place="margin">The Text refers her extraction to <hi>Syrophae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicia,</hi> the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and as ſuch was under stood by this</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gentile not Greek</hi>) The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> (comprizing the Patriarchs their progenitours) were reduced to wait four hundred &amp; thirty years, ere they were introduced into the promis'd Land:
<note place="margin">Gal 3.17.</note> and during a great part of that long ſpace of time, languiſh'd and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48185:32"/>groan'd under the heavy Burthens, and other as heavy preſſures, of the as cruelly as unſucceſſefully politick <hi>Aegyptians.</hi> St.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 28.24. 2 Cor. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf pray'd the Lord thrice, for the removall of that rude <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Thorn to the fleſh</hi> (whatſoever that may mean.) Nay of the bleſſed Virgin-Mother her ſelfe her divine Son would not be found till the third day,
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.48</note> though ſhe ſought him ſorrowing. And <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to whom even during his ſickneſſe he vouchſafed (a Title to which all <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>'s were but Trifles) the ſtyle of Friend,
<note place="margin">Joh. 11.2.</note> which emboldned the pious <hi>Mary</hi> to paraphraſe him by a,
<note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Hee whom thou loveſt,</hi> was permitted not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lye a dying, but to dye; his Reſcue being deferr'd till it was thought Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; and was ſo indeed, to any leſs power then Omnipotence. Which manifeſts, that as no degree of Diſtreſs is unrelievable by his power; ſo no extreamity of it, is inconſiſtent with his compasſion, no nor with his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. He whoſe ſpirit inſpired the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.3.</note> is in the laſt of them repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented under the Notion of a Refiner: and 'tis not the Cuſtome of Refiners to ſnatch the belov'd Mettall out of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48185:33"/>the fire, as ſoon as it feels the violence of that purifying Element, nay nor as ſoon as it is melted by it, but they let it long indure the brunt of the active flames, actuated by exciting Blaſts, till it have ſtood its due time in the fire, and there obtain'd its full purity and ſplendor. And I hope you will give a converſer with Furnaces (though no pretender to the Philoſopher's Stone) leave to improve a Chymicall Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, and obſerve, that though in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, eſpecially Nationall or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Calamities, God oftentimes ſeems to make no diſtinction betwixt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his compaſſion and thoſe of his fury, indiſcriminately involving them in the ſame deſtiny; yet his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and intentions make a vaſt Difference, where his inflictions ſeem not to make any: As, when on the ſame Teſt, and with the ſelf-ſame Fire, we urge (as well) the Gold as the blended Lead or Antimony; but with fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing and deſigning ſuch a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the events, as to conſume the Ignobler Mineralls or blow them off into droſſe or fumes, and make the Gold more pure and full of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48185:33"/>
            <p>It is true, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>9</label> and (not to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of partiality towards a Love, which ſo little needs it, to be thought fit to be praeferr'd before all other paſſions) I ſhall acknowledge it, that the happineſſe, reſulting from thoſe many prerogatives, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to diſcover to you in a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent degree of <hi>Seraphick Love,</hi> is moderated by the Effects of that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limity, the Eager Deſires, it creates of a more compleat fruition of its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and divine Object. Such aſpiring Salleys of the longing Soul, made the languiſhing Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> cry out, <hi>Stay me with Flaggons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 11.5</note> 
               <hi>Comfort me with Apples; for I am ſick of Love.</hi> Such made the raviſht <hi>Apostle</hi> deſire <hi>to return</hi> (for ſo I ſhould rather tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there,
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> and ſo I find it
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.36.</note> elſewhere to fignifie) <hi>and to be with Chriſt:</hi> and the Inſpir'd Poet thus expreſſes his longings to the bleſſed Object of them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>As the Hart panteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the water-Brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee O God. My Soul thirſteth for God, for the living God: when ſhall I come and appear before God.</hi> But, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> it was fit, that to elevate our thoughts and wiſhes to Heaven, ſome peculiar
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48185:34"/>and elſewhere incommunicable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Joy, ſhould be reſerv'd for us there. And 'tis a good ſign, and ſuch as worldly Objects cannot boaſt, when the Incompleatneſſe of our Seraphick Lover's happineſſe in his fruitions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from their want of Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorineſſe, but his want of an Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Poſſesſion of them. And let me tell you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that even this uneaſie ſtate of Separation, is ſweetned with as much allay as is conſiſtent with its being a Grief. For, the Divine Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and teacher of Gods love, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing a thirſt after perfection to be a Title to it (according to thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirst after Righteouſneſſe: for, they ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.17.</note> And, <hi>Let him that is a thirst come and whoſoever will let him take of the water of Life freely</hi>) and the Joyes of Heaven being ſo vaſt, that they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their Nature to all the grounded Hopes, men have to enjoy them; each new Aſſuranc is a new Degree of them, and is acceptable to our hope though uneaſie to our deſires. And theſe bait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at compleat felicity ſhould not be more unwelcome for the preſent diſquiet they ſuppoſe, than the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48185:34"/>for the Zeal they argue, and the Felicity, they promiſe: For, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the Spirit in our hearts may be juſtly termed, at the Spirit himſelf in Scripture, is, <hi>An earneſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.5</note> which though by being ſuch, it confeſſes it ſelf not to be the Entire ſumme, yet is not onely a Part of it, but a Pledge: And, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> how Supportable is this thus-qualified Allay of the Joyes of <hi>Seraphick Love,</hi> in compariſon of the Diſquiets and the Torments, that are wont to attend ſenſuall Love? I ſhall not loſe time to enumerate, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it is ſuppoſed to have ſent to their Graves: becauſe, though I find thoſe Tragicall ſtories rife enough in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, yet I find them rarities every where but in thoſe Fabulous compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: and though I have had the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to viſit ſome of thoſe warmer Regions, where the Flames of Love are thought to burne with more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, yet (bating by Duells and the Pox) I remember not to have obſerv'd Love to have ever been the Death of any man: unleſſe, ſpeaking like Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, who make Reaſon the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Conſtituent Form of man, we will affirm that Love by dethroning
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48185:35"/>Reaſon, though it leave the Lover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, doth kill the Man. But though I am loath to put ſo bad a Complement upon mankind, as to ſay, that Love is wont to deſtroy mens lives; yet I think it would be no Calumnie to ſay, It much diſquiets them. I could ask you, How long many a Lover muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a Servant to purchaſe the honour of being taken notice of to be ſo? And I could recruite that Queſtion with pretty ſtore of others of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but that I ſuppoſe, your memory will ſave my Pen the labour of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to you the Torments of Love, which they that feel them, would lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſſe juſtly, then they do frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtyle Martyrdoms, if the Greatneſſe onely, without the Cauſe and Object of Mens ſufferings ſuffic'd to make them Martyrs. And though the Condition of Lovers be in Romances ſo dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and delightfully deſcrib'd, that not onely Sanguine Readers are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, but even I my ſelf have been ſurpriſed into Inclinations to admire and envie their Felicity; yet when ſome I was concern'd for, have been really concern'd and engaged in ſuch adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, my Envy quickly turned into
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48185:35"/>Pitty. For the repulſes, the regrets, the jealouſies, the fears, the abſences, the deſpairs, and the reſt of the afflicting diſquiets of Lovers: though in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Romances, they are ſoon read over by the diverted peruſer; yet they are not ſo ſoon weather'd out, nor ſo eaſily ſupported, by the diſconſolate Lover: whoſe infelicities, though they may be perhaps ſo handſomly deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as to delight the Reader; yet, truſt me, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> 'Tis a much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier condition to be free from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, than to be able to complain eloquently of them. And as I have with delight beheld a ſtorm, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently drawn by ſome rare Artiſt's Penſill; but when I was this Spring toſt by the rude winds, that blew me out of <hi>Holland,</hi> I found a reall Storm, a very troubleſome and uneaſie thing. So the condition of a Lover, (whoſe happineſſe depends on the conſtancy, of what, perhaps, you have found as fickle, as either Winds or Seas, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Heart) though drawn by a ſmooth Pen, it is wont ſtrangely to affect and pleaſe us; yet when men are really engaged in it, they find it full of hardſhips and diſquiet. 'Tis a much
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48185:36"/>better condition to be look'd on, than embrac'd; and Experience gives men of it much (ſadder and) more unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come notions, then Deſcription did. Nor phancie, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomeneſſe of your ſufferings in love, proceeded but from their not being acceptable to her, for whom you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured them; for, had your Miſtreſſe crowned them with Myrtle, and prov'd as kind to you as <hi>Hymen</hi> could have made her; yet, I fear, ſhe could have Recompenced you but by Diſabuſing you, and could not have freed you from the Need of happineſſe, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from a Miſtake of it. For me-thinks, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> moſt of theſe tranſitory Goods that we are ſo fond of, may not unfitly be reſmbled to the Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Plant, which you have admired at <hi>Sion</hi>-Garden; for, as, though we gaze on it with attention and wonder, yet when we come to touch it, the coy deluſive Plant immediately ſhrinks in its diſplayed leaves, and contracts it ſelf into a form and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, diſadvantagiouſly differing from the former; which it again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers by degrees, when toucht no longer: So theſe objects, that charm us
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48185:36"/>at a diſtance, and whilſt gaz'd on with the eyes of expectation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; when a more immediate poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath put them into our hands, their former luſtre vaniſhes, and they appear quite differing things from what before they ſeem'd; though after deprivation or abſence hath made us forget their emptineſſe, and we be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to look upon them again at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, they recover in moſt mens eyes their former beauty, and are as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as before to inveagle &amp; delude us. I muſt add, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that when I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to the Senſitive Plant moſt of theſe tranſitory things, that are flattered with the title of Goods, I do not out of that number except moſt Miſtreſſes. For though I am no ſuch enemy to Matrimony, as ſome (for want of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the Raillery, I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times us'd in ordinary diſcourſe) are pleaſed to think me; and would not refuſe you my Advice (though I would not ſo readily give you my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) to turn Votary to <hi>Hymen;</hi> yet I have obſerved ſo few Happy Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſo many Unfortunate ones; and have ſo rarely ſeen men love their wives at the rate they did, whilſt they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48185:37"/>were than Miſtreſſes, that I wonder not, that Legiſlators thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make marriages Indiſſoluble, to make them Laſting. And I canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fitlier compare Marriage than to a Lottery; for in both, he that ventures may ſucceed, and may miſſe; and if he draw a prize, he hath a rich Return o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Venture: But in both Lotteries, there lye a pretty ſtore of Blancks for every Prize. And for your particular, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> the world is much miſtaken in both your humours, if <hi>Hermione</hi>'s and yours be not ſo unſuitable, that (to make haſte from ſo nice a ſubject) had ſhe juſtified your expectation of her kindneſſe, you would have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed the Perſon without poſſeſſing the Happineſſe you expected: And might have found your ſelf, as ſenſibly diſappointed by her Grant, as you were by her Change.</p>
            <p>But I forget, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, not to inſiſt on Parallels, and therefore, inſtead of proſecuting the diſcourſe my Pen has ſlip't into, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the advantages of <hi>Seraphick,</hi> compared with ordinary Love; I ſhall venture to incourage you to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by ſhowing you, that your paſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48185:37"/>addictedneſſe to the later, may prove ſerviceable to you in it: Yes, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> I ſhall not ſcruple to tell you, that your ſtrong Paſſion for <hi>Hermione,</hi> may not a little facilitate your Devotion, by breaking all the Chains, excepting one, that faſtned your Affection to unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Objects, and reſtrain'd it from ſoaring to the ſublimeſt, and by exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your Paſſion to a Height fit for <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphick</hi> flames. For, Love hath this of Noble, that it makes us deveſt our ſelves of ſelfiſhneſſe; ſlight fortune, quiet, ſafety, honour, life, and all our owne Concernments, when their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Competition with the Lov'd partie's Intereſts, may render their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice acceptable to Her: and to think Goods or Ills deſerve thoſe names, but as they come to us from, or through Her. You could ſcarce have learn't a better Leſſon, even from a much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Maſter; for, Love having thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed you, to (what is thought moſt difficult in that vertue) the Acts of ſelfe-deniall, you need almoſt, but Transferre your flames from an Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and miſtaken, to their True &amp; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Object, and you will have exalted and refined your Love into Devotion;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48185:38"/>to the latter, of which, a ſublime Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varion of the firſt, is ſuch a diſpoſition, as the having formerly by looſer Aires, and (perchance) wanton Songs, learn't to Improve and to Command ones voice, is to the skill of Singing, thoſe devour Hymnes and heavenly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themes, in which the Church-Militant ſeems ambitious to emulate the Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and Eccho back the ſolemne Praiſes and Hallelujahs of the Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Quire. And, as by Hunting, though (poſſibly) we follow but ſome poore fugitive Hare, or ſome ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling game, we gain that Vigour, that Sufferance, and Agility, that fit us for the Toyles, and Military hard-ſhips, that are exacted in the purſuit of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of Empire: ſo though in Love, (Devotion's Prentice-ſhip) the Courted Creature be often inconſiderable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to make our Elections fit to be numbered amongſt ſuch, as thoſe that made Love be painted Blind; yet in the Progreſſe and Conduct of our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we contract ſuch diſ-intereſts and reſign'd Habitudes, as, being preferr'd to ſerve Coeleſtiall Objects, do excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently qualifie us for Devotion. And, in effect, a fervent Love ſeems little elſe,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48185:38"/>then Devotion miſ-addreſt, where our owne very expreſſions may ſerve to diſabuſe us; For, when you give your Miſtriſs the ſtyle of Goddeſſe, and talke of nothing to her, but Offering up of hearts, Adoring, Sacrifices, Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; does not all this imply, that, though it be ſaid to her, 'tis meant to a Divinity: which is ſo much the true and genuine Object of men's Love, that we cannot exalt that paſſion for any other, without inveſting it with the Notion and Attributes of God? As Children diſcloſe the inbred kindneſſe they have for thoſe Perſons, by calling the Babies, they moſt doat upon, by their dear Mothers,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32. verſ. 4, 5. In the latter of which it is expreſly ſaid, that the Feaſt was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>To Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> the peculiar Name of the true God.</note> or lov'd Nurſes Names. And as <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Jewes, by juſtifying to themſelves their Adoration of the Idols they had ſet up, by attributing the Title of God to what they ador'd, did tacitly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Adoration to be due onely to the Deity: ſo, does a Lover by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what he Worſhips, a Divinity, tacitly confeſſe the Deity to be the proper Object, of that higheſt and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar ſtraine of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>And this truth, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>8</label> the very ſickleneſſe of Lovers concurrs to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48185:39"/>for what men call and think, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, is nothing but a Chaſe of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Beauty, which our Love fruitleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows, and ſeeks in ſeverall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, becauſe he finds it not entire in any one; for, Creatures have but ſmall and obſcure fragments of it, which cannot fix nor ſatisfie an Appetite, born for, and (though unknowingly) aſpiring unto God: who is proclaimed the true and proper Object of our Love, as well by mens fickleneſſe to women, as the Angells conſtancy to Him. Juſt as the trembling reſtleſneſſe of the Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in any but the North point of the Compaſſe, proceeds from, and manifeſts its Inclination to the Pole, its Paſsion for which, both its wavering and its reſt, bear equall witneſſe to. That unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'dneſſe with tranſitory fruitions, that men deplore as the Unhappineſs of their Nature, is indeed the Priviledge of it; as 'tis the Praerogative of men, not to care for, or be capable of being pleaſ'd with Whiſtles, Hobby-horſes, and ſuch fond Toyes as Children doat upon, and make the ſole objects of their Deſires and Joyes. And by this you may, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> in ſome degree imagine the unimaginable ſuavity,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48185:39"/>that the fixing of ones Love on God, is able to bleſſe the Soul with, ſince by ſo indulgent a Father, and Competent a Judge, as God himſelf; the decree'd uncontentingneſſe of all other goods is thought richly repaired by its being but an Aptneſſe, to prove a Riſe to our Love's ſetling there.</p>
            <p>And hitherto, my deareſt <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>9</label> I have endeavour'd, to recommend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you <hi>Seraphick</hi> Love, by mentioning ſome of its Properties, which ſeem to relate more to the Love it ſelfe, then to the divine Object of it. But I feare you'l think, I have too long entertain'd you with Conſiderations, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that they are not altogether the importanteſt, that belong to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; I have been by haſte reduc'd to Pen in the unaccurate Order, wherein they offer'd themſelves to my thoughts, not the Method wherein I ſhould have preſented them to yours.</p>
            <p>And therefore, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>10</label> ſince the Nobleſt and ſupream Motives to the love of God, conſiſt in his own infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perfections and Prerogatives; and ſince the properties of God's Love to us do advantage us much more, (and conſequently are likelier to endear
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48185:40"/>Devotion to us) than thoſe of ours to him: The former not onely moving God to Kindle in us, but to Cheriſh and Foment, and, if our own wilfull extinction interpoſe not, to Crown the latter: for both theſe reaſons, I ſay, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> I doubt not, but you'l think it ſeaſonable for me to proceed, to conſider that higher ſort of Motives to Devotion; and to evince, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall things, which are wont moſt to Engage and Heighten our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do, in a peculiar and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant manner, ſhine forth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellate in God: That, you know, which enamour'd you of <hi>Hermione,</hi> I need not prove to you, to have been your ſuppoſing her full of Lovelineſſe and Excellencies in her ſelf; and your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that the Love ſhe vouchſafed you was Great, Free, Conſtant, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to you. And that all theſe properties do not onely eminently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt, but illuſtriouſly concur in God, and in his Love; I muſt now, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> (with ſtrong deſires of doing it Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly) attempt to manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt then,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>11</label> our higheſt love is made God's due by the Excellencie and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of his Nature. But truſt me, <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48185:40"/>when (necesſitated by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, exacted by the nature of this diſcourſe) I find my ſelf engaged to ſay ſomething, by way of celebration of Gods Perfections: I am very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I can but Detract from what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to Praiſe, and muſt unevitably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unable to ſpeak worthily of a Theme, to which even Seraphims themſelves cannot do right. And if, as the Scripture aſſures us, thoſe things neither fell under the Senſes nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Thoughts of men,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> which God has reſerv'd for thoſe that love him; how ineffable and incomprehenſible muſt thoſe things be, which he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd for himſelf; the infinite Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of his Nature above all Created Beings, placing a vaſt diſparity betwixt his greateſt communicated Vouchſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his Boundleſs, and therefore to creatures Incommunicable, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p>Wonder not therefore, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that my weak eyes dare not dwell long upon an Object, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtedfaſtly gaze on long, without being dazl'd: And do not marvaile, that I ſcruple not, to uſe ſeeming Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolies in the mention of perfections,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48185:41"/>which make the higheſt Hyperbolies but Seeming ones. Both Gods Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and his Word declaring him to be <hi>exalted above all bleſſing and praiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 9.5.</note> If it were ſeaſonable, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain our ſelves but with thoſe attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, which are Legible or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in the Creation, We might there diſcern the admirable Traces of ſuch immenſe Power, ſuch unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wiſdome, and ſuch exuberant Goodneſſe as may juſtly raviſh us to an amazement at them and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. And I muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that when with bold Teleſcopes, I ſurvay the old and newly diſcovered Starrs and Planets that adorn the upper Region of the World; and when with excellent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſcopes I diſcern in otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Objects the unimitable Subtlety of Nature's Curious Workmanſhip; And when, in a word, by the help of Anatomicall Knives, and the light of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>micall Furnaces, I ſtudy the Book of Nature, and conſult the Gloſſes of <hi>Ariſtotle, Epicurus, Paracelſus, Harvey, Helmont,</hi> and other learn'd Expoſitors of that inſtructive Volumne; I find my ſelf oftentimes reduc'd to exclaim
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48185:41"/>with the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 104.24</note> 
               <hi>How manifold are thy works, O Lord? in wiſdom hast thou made them all.</hi> And when I have been loſing my ſelf in admiration of what I Underſtand but enough to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and not to Comprehend; I am of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten obliged to interrupt or break off my Enquiries by applying to the works of Gods Creation, the Expreſſion us'd by St. <hi>Paul</hi> of thoſe of his Providence, <hi>O the Depth of the Riches both of the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge of God!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 21.33.</note> 
               <hi>how unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his Judgments, and his wayes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traceable:</hi> And Exclamations of this Nature may the attentive Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of any other of Gods Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes deſervedly produce. But having elſewhere treated of this ſubject in a Peculiar Diſcourſe: I ſhall now, <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi> invite you to conſider with me how much You, and thoſe that are Conſcious to their having Vertue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in themſelves to make them prize it in others, are in Love with <hi>Cato, Scipio,</hi> and thoſe other <hi>Heroe's</hi> that did enoble and almoſt exceed mankind upon the bare knowledge of their vertues; although, from them wee derive no Perſonall advantage (their Death having numerous ages
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48185:42"/>preceded our Nativity.) Since then we pay ſo much diſintereſt-Love to ſome few faint and ill refin'd Vertues, that ne're did profit us: how much on ſuch a Score, and at that Rate, ſhould we Love him, who ſo poſſeſſes All perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that each of his Perfections is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite? Were you and I our own Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> and wholly Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent upon God, without either Need or Hope to taſte his Bounty; his native Excellencies, and what he has done for others, ſhould ſurely raviſh us and enamour us of Him. Though his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to us did not entitle him to our Love, his Eſſence (the Source and only Motive of thoſe Benefits) would give him a right to it; and though we ow'd him nought for what We are, we yet ſhould owe him Love for what He is. He is that glorious Sun From whom (as beams) all created-perfections flow, and In whom they all concenter. To omit God's Soveraign Majeſty (which places him ſo high, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at but to own for him ſo familiar and levelling an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as Love much more to expect to be re-lov'd by him, were not the leaſt ſawcie Preſumption man could be guilty of, did not his own Commands
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48185:42"/>make it a Duty.) Not to inſiſt on this, I ſay; Let us a while conſider that proper and peculiar attractive of Love, his Lovelineſs; which is ſuch, that, did we but once ſee it, all Creature-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions (ev'n we being Judges) would then be as Impoſſible, as they are now Unjuſt. In <hi>the fifth Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt's</hi> prophetick Viſion,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 6.7.</note> the Scraphims themſelves, thoſe glorious Ornaments of the Coeleſtiall Hierarchie, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as covering their faces in Gods preſence, either bluſhing at their Comparative Deformity, or unable to ſuſtain the unqualifi'd Spl<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>edor of ſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine a Brightnes; whence perhaps it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of old the Jewiſh faſhion (as ſome frequent Expreſſions in their Writers intimate) when they went to Pray, to Vaile their head and faces: (though now I have in their Synagogues ſeen them only cover their heads, not their faces, with thoſe white Garments they wear, at their publick devotions:) And,<hi>Lindamor,</hi> if <hi>Moſes</hi>'s face by but a few dayes converſe with God, reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch a light as dazl'd mortall eyes; and if his ſwift poſts, the Angels, when ſent on Errants to us here on Earth, even when they may be ſuppos'd (if
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48185:43"/>I may ſo ſpeak) to weare their Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Cloaths, and ſtoop as much to our frailty in the Form, as in the Region, they appear to us in, do, in ſpight of that darkning Condeſcenſion, ſo much Tranſcend all Objects here on Earth, that the Scripture often mentions, That even thoſe that Aſpir'd to imitate their Vertues, were confounded at their Preſence: And if, in this vailing Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit they appear ſo Glorious, that their thus diſadvantag'd Beauty is made the Complement and Hyperbole of that Quality: what may we, or rather what may we not, conclude of God himſelf, of whom the Scripture ſays, <hi>He that planted the Eare ſhall he not hear?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.9.</note> He that formed the Eye ſhall he not ſee?</hi> That is, he that imparts a faculty or an Excellence to the Creature, ſhall not he himſelf much more eminently poſſeſſe it? And in effect, the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſhed Created Beauties are but faint Shadows (or trulier, Foyles) of His. Thoſe drops of Prettineſſe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teringly ſprinkled amongſt the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were deſign'd to defaecate and exalt our Conceptions, not to inveagle or deteine our Paſſions; for, God did ne're intend them to terminate our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48185:43"/>Love, but only by our Eyes to exalt our Faith above them, and by the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, our ſight can apprehend, to raiſe us to a Confidence, that there is in their Author more than we can either ſee, or comprehend.
<note place="margin">2 King. 2.11.</note> Like <hi>Elijahs</hi> fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, though they be Pure and Bright and conſiſt of the refulgenteſt materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, they are meant by God but to carry us up to him. And as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch's Steward was furniſh'd with ſo ſumptuous an Equipage,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.10.53.</note> to court <hi>Rebecca,</hi> not for himſelfe, but for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſo all the Lovelineſſe impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Creature, is lent it, but to give us ſome more enlarg'd concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that vaſt Confluence and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity that exuberates in God. To make the righteſt uſe of Fadeing beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, you muſt conſider God and them, as you were wont to do your Miſtriſſe's Picture, and its Cryſtall Cover: where though that native Glaſſe were pure and Lovely, and very richly edg'd; yet to gaze on it, was not the Chiefeſt Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your Eye; nor did you in it Terminate your ſight, but greedily look through and Beyond it, upon th'd ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Image, that ſolid vail betray'd. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, <hi>Seraphick</hi> and our common <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> behold exteriour beauties with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48185:44"/>a Difference reſembling that, where with Children and Aſtronomers conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Galileo</hi>'s Optick Glaſſes, (with one of which <hi>Teleſcopioes,</hi> that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I ſaw at <hi>Florence,</hi> he merrily booſted that he had, <hi>Trovato la Corte a Gione</hi>) which th' one prizes moſt, for what they Appear; the other, for what they Diſcover. For Children contenting themſelves to wonder at the Length, and fall in Love with the Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Gildings of the Tube, do thus but Gaze Upon them, whereas Aſtronomers Look Through them, and, ſcarce taking notice of the unuſuall Ornaments, or the ſhape, imploy them to find out unknown Lights in the Skie, and to deſcry in Heaven bright Stars, unſeen before, and other Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Novelties and Beauties.</p>
            <p>I deny not,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>12</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that God has been pleaſ'd to adorn ſome of his Creatures with Hints and Impreſſes, as well of His Lovelineſſe, as his other Excellencies; But they do much more faintly and imperfectly reſemble him, than the Counterfeit Sun, we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſee in a Cloud, aemulates the True one, by whoſe Refracted or reflected Beams, ſome acute moderne
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48185:44"/>Naturaliſts ſuppoſe it to be produc'd. For though, this Derivative Sun ſhine with a not-inconſiderable Luſtre, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively to the reſt of the dark Cloud it ennoble's, yet is it not onely as much inferiour to the true Sun in Brightneſſe, as in Height; but it enjoyes alone, a Precarious, Dependent, and almoſt Momentany Being, which often it loſes in a very Short time, and never attains to preſerve a very Long one. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to neglect that ſupream Reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, that ſhines in God, for thoſe dimm Repreſentations of it, that we ſo doat on in the Creatures, is as praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous and abſured; as it were for a Perſian to offer his Sacrifice to a Parhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, (as the Greeks call that Meteor) inſtead of adoring the Sun. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> if our dim ſight, like that of the Prophet's Servant,
<note place="margin">2 King 6.27.</note> who ſaw the Mountain near <hi>Dothan</hi> cover'd with Horſes and Chariots of Fire, were priviledg'd to diſcern Inviſible Objects; our raviſht Eyes would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Lovelineſſe enough in God, to make us inceſſantly exclaim, in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Prophet; <hi>How great is his Goodneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9.17</note> 
               <hi>and how great his Beauty?</hi> Agreeably whereunto, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48185:45"/>That as the Load-ſtone, doth at tract moſt powerfully the brighteſt Needles, made of the pureſt Steel, and thoſe that moſt approach it; ſo Angells, who of all Created Beings enjoy the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloudedſt light &amp; the moſt clear know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their Maker, do love him with a Conſtancy ſo fix't, that in five thouſand and ſome odde Centuries of yeares, (efflux't ſince the Creation) they could never ſee any thing, either in God, or out of Him, Capable to ſeduce them to a Change. Gods Lovelineſs, (which is ſuch, that the eternall Fruition of himſelfe, Create sev'n His faelicity) is like rare Muſick, which though it do delight all its partakers, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing'ſt Artiſts ſtill do highlieſt value, and are moſt raviſh't with; The Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports it produceth, being proportion'd to the degrees of the Skillfulneſſe of its admirers. The Apoſtate Spirits indeed deſerted their firſt Station, not frighted thence by any blemiſh they deſcry'd in God; but probably fell by a ſawcy affectation of a Parity, and (as Divines tell us) a Sacrilegious aſpiring to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which they were criminally unable to behold, without wiſhing them their owne. And for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48185:45"/>ſeparation from God, it is their Curſe and Puniſhment: And I ſhall ingenuouſly confeſſe to you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that by the advantagious Idea's I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd of Gods Perfections, I have been ſometimes inclin'd to think, that the reaſon, why God tells <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou canſt not ſee my face, for there ſhall no man ſee me, and live,</hi> might be, that (as Tranſcendent Objects deſtroy the Senſe) ſo Lovely and Glorious a ſight, (whoſe Continuance ſhall make our Happineſſe in Heaven) would let in Joyes, and would create Deſires, too mighty for frail Mortality to ſuſtain; the raviſh't Soul, being ſhown ſuch Game, as That, would bate ſo eagerly, that ſhe would break thoſe Leaches that tye her to the Bodie, (and thereby, hinder her flight to that wiſh't union) and the glad Heart, (too narrow a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle for ſo much Joy) to make room for ſuch Gueſts, would ſtretch unto a Rupture. Longing or Joy, have ſometimes ſingly reach't Degrees, that have made them Fatall; And why then ſhould their Union in ſuch Extreams, be thought uncapable of producing the like effect? Nor is it perchance more a Priviledge of the next Life, that we
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48185:46"/>ſhall then ſee God; than, that we ſhall ſurvive that glorious Sight: which is too dazling an Object for Mortall Eyes, till (to uſe St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Expreſſion) <hi>our mortall Part have put on Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.54.</note> But I muſt no longer loſe my ſelf in a Theme, on which it is ſo eaſie to ſpeak Much, and ſo impoſſible to ſay Enough. If I be not very much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they are ſo; who preſume to give us ſatisfactory Definitions of Gods Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which we may perhaps more ſafely define, by the Impoſſibility of its being accurately defined; And I muſt confeſſe, I do the leaſt expect the beſt Deſcription of the Divine Nature from thoſe, that are moſt forward, to take upon them to explicate it: For our Words being but the Repreſentations of our Notions, and they being neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily Finite, as our Being; few men are (me-thinks) more likely to be miſtaken in the Nature of what's Infinite, (and conſequently of Gods Attributes) than thoſe that think Deſcriptions can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize it. Nor will an Aſſiduity and Conſtancy of our Speculations herein relieve us; For too fix't a Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Eſſence, does but the more Confound us. As I remember, St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48185:46"/>tells the Jewes,
<note place="margin">Act. 22.6, 11.</note> that he <hi>could not ſee for the Glory of that light,</hi> that ſhone from Heaven about him at his Converſion. And this the famous <hi>Simonides</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally found, who being ask't, What God was, took a dayes time to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it; after, being call'd upon for his anſwer, he deſir'd two dayes longer to think upon it; and, when they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd, demanded four dayes longer; and ſo continu'd a great while, each time encreaſing his Demands for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite: till, being preſt to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſuch a Dilatory way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, he ingenuouſly acknowledg'd, that the longer he Conſider'd Gods Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the leſs he Comprehended it. And indeed, Experience teacheth us, that they, that gaze ſtedfaſtlieſt on the noon dayes Sunne, can leaſt of all diſcern what it is, being rather Dazl'd, then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by ſo confounding an Object; Nor is it onely, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> a task of too great Difficulty for a mere man, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to Explicate that Incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature of God, to which nothing but his own Infinite Underſtanding can be adequate. But, me-thinks, even to Celebrate Gods perfections, cannot be ſoberly attempted without a very deep
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48185:47"/>ſenſe of a mans own Unworthineſſe and Incapacity. For, the ſame Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that furniſh us with Praiſes, do tranſcend them. And the fruitfulneſſe of the Subject may as well deterr, as invite our Pens; ſince, as we are ſure we ſhall not Want Theme, ſo we are certain, we cannot Dignifie it. And for my part, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> though my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject exacted of me, the Praiſes I have endeavoured to aſcribe to God, yet I ſhould have thought it requiſiite, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to decline the Laws of Method; than be reduced to derogate from what I would extoll: if the Neceſſity of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting from God's Perfections, were not equall to that of Mentioning them; and if that Neceſſity were not as Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to God, as greater Praiſes than we are able to aſcribe him, could be. But, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> having thus done right to my Method, though I could not to my Theme, I ſhall onely invite you to imitate with me thoſe Perſians, that adored the Sun, though the light he lent them ſerv'd but to make the ſource of it admired, and not to pry into his abſtruſe Eſſence with it. And though I might ſay much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God's Perfections, I muſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48185:47"/>henceforth think Silence the propereſt Language I can now employ; for 'tis Silence that beſt expreſſes our wonder: and, ſure, wonder is never more ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, then when God is the Object; A proſtrate Veneration being the ſafeſt Apprehenſion of Him, that is Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible.</p>
            <p>Having thus conſidered, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> how fit an Object God is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>13</label> of our higheſt Love, for what he is in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Let us now proceed to derive further proofs of the ſame I ruth, from what he is to Us, (that your Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude may contend with your Reaſon, which ſhall more heighten your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion) and we ſhall find in the Vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Freeneſſe, Diſ-intereſtneſſe, Conſtancy, and Advantagiouſneſſe of his Love to us, that more than All the Love we can pay him, were but a little Part of that we owe him.</p>
            <p>But for the firſt Attribute, we have aſſigned his Love (the Greatneſſe of it) it being a Generall property, diffuſed through all the reſt, and conſpicuous in them, it requires not to be treated of apart.</p>
            <p>We ſhall then proceed to the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48185:48"/>or unmeritedneſſe of God's love; To believe which, ſtrangely vaſt, we need but conſider, that we ſo little could at firſt Deſerve his love, that he lov'd us even before we had a beeing: And our Felicity, in his Decrees, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded our Exiſtence in this world. God lov'd you numerous ages before you were; and his Goodneſſe is ſo entirely its own Motive, that even your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſince when alone, you can pretend to merit his love) is the Effect of it. This Benefit alone were ſufficient, to render God the Object of our Love, though We were that of his Averſion. For (as the Perſians ador'd the Sun, even when it ſchorch'd them) we eſteem our ſelves obliged to Love and honour our Parents, in ſpight of their being wicked and unkind; though they be but God's Inſtruments in our Production, and made us what we were born, not Arbitrarily, but in vertue of his Ordination. But God, to confer on us, in the moſt excellent and endearing manner, the bleſſing promiſed to his antient People, when he vouchſafed to aſſure them,
<note place="margin">Hoſ 14.4.</note> that <hi>he would love them freely,</hi> was pleaſed to love us, not onely when we were not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48185:48"/>at all, but when we were his Enemies: <hi>If when we were enemies</hi> (ſaith St.
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son,</hi> &amp;c. Our inexiſtence indeed was a condition, wherein nothing in us was capable of being a Motive of God's Love: but our Enmity proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made us Worthy of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation; as if his Love were nothing, unleſſe it Vanquiſh'd Obſtacles, as well as Wanted Motives. This gave the Apoſtle a juſt cauſe to ſay,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> that <hi>God commendeth his love towards us, in that while we were yet ſinners Christ dyed for us:</hi> That is, when we wanted all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to invite his Love, unleſſe our very Want of them ſhould paſſe for one. And how did God expreſſe his Love unto us? Even by the Gift of the Son of his love; <hi>For God ſo loved the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.16.</note> (ſaies the divine Token of his Love) <hi>that he gave his onely begotten Son.</hi> And how did that Son love it? <hi>He</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle) <hi>being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God; but made himſelf of no reputation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men. And being found in faſhion as a man, he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf, and became obedient unto
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48185:49"/>death, even the death of the Croſſe.</hi> That is, That he would love at no leſſe Rate than Death; and from the ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent heighth of Glory, ſtoopt and abas'd himſelf to the ſufferance of the extreameſt of Indignities, and ſunk himſelf to the bottom of Abjected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to exalt our condition to the contrary Extream.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> 
               <hi>He was wounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and with his stripes we are healed,</hi> ſaies the Prophet. <hi>For ye know the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>that though he was rich, yet for your ſakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be made rich,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle. Men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpleaſed God, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forfeited all right and Naturall Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility to happineſſe; even whilſt they compleated the Forlornneſſe of their condition, by the Lethargy of not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible of it, and were as careleſſe to ſeek means of recovery, as they had been unable to deviſe them of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Even then, his reſtleſſe Love would never be at quiet, till it had ſet his Omnipotence on work, to contrive Expedients, and find out a way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile his Juſtice and his Mercy, in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48185:49"/>reconciling Sinners to Himſelf. And this mercifull Deſigne, by the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Son, he proſecuted in a way ſo Worthy of Himſelf, &amp; ſo Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to us, that our juſt wonder at it may keep us from having any, to find that, as <hi>St. Peter</hi> informs us, the very Angels (prompted queſtionleſſe, by a Religious Curioſity) ardently <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to look into</hi> thoſe Divine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.12.</note> I find it hotly diſputed amongſt Divines, (not onely betwixt the Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the Orthodox, but betwixt Orthodox and Orthodox) Whether or no God could, without violating his Juſtice, have deviſed any other Courſe for the Expiation of Sin, than the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Death of Chriſt. But, without venturing to Determine, whether or no God Could, to Redeem us, have choſen any other way, We may ſafely think, that he Has choſen the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging and moſt endearing way, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing in this Divine Manner of reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing us, the ſevereſt Juſtice, and the higheſt Mercy; the greateſt Hatred of Sin, and the greateſt Love to Sinners: Since by thoſe unequald' &amp; unvalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sufferings, to which he delivered up for us that Son, who is ſo near unto
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48185:50"/>him, that he truly ſaid, <hi>I and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are one,</hi> He at once manifeſted both how much he Hated Sin, which he ſo heavily Puniſh'd in the Perſon, he moſt Lov'd, though that Surety but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted it, to free men from the Inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable vengeance of it; and How much he Lov'd Sinners by giving up what he ſo lov'd for a Ranſome of thoſe, that were guilty of what he ſo hated. And therefore our Saviour, though he did ſuch great things to ſatisfie the unbelieving and contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Jews of his being their promis'd <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> would not decline death to convince them; And, though he had not ſeldom done ſo much to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Object of their Faith, would not be invited from the Croſſe, though the chief Prieſts and Scribes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſaid,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.7.</note> at his Crucifixion, <hi>Let him him now come down from the Croſſe, and we will believe on him:</hi> And Chriſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the World of their unableneſſe to emerge and recover out of that deep Abyſſe, wherein the Load of ſin (which in Scripture is call'd <hi>a weight</hi>) had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated fallen Man,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> came not into the World untill well nigh 4000. years of ſickneſſe had made the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48185:50"/>Deſperate, and the cure almoſt Hopeleſſe. So inveterate an obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy at once widening the Diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Man, and proclaiming the latter's Diſability, to finde by his own wiſdom Expedients of Re-union: Thus Chriſt heal'd and diſpoſſeſſ'd a dumb perſon,
<note place="margin">Mat. 9.32.</note> who was able to make entreaties but by the Diſability of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing them; and might truly ſay to the ſecure World,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.1.</note> 
               <hi>I am found of them that ſought me not:</hi> And when our Saviour Was come into the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched World, of all the numerous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles recorded in the Goſpel, he ſcarce did any for his own private Relief: And to ſhew, that, as he endured his Sorrows for our ſakes,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> that <hi>by his stripes</hi> we might <hi>be healed;</hi> ſo were the Joyes, he taſted in Relation to Us. We read not (which is highly obſervable) in the whole Goſpell that ever he Rejoyc'd but once; and that was, when his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd Diſciples inform'd him, that they had Victoriouſly <hi>chaſ'd Devills</hi> and <hi>diſeaſes</hi> out of <hi>oppreſſed Mortalls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk: 10.</note> and that by his <hi>Authority</hi> men had been <hi>diſpoſſeſs'd</hi> of both the Temptor and Puniſhment of Sin. He converſt among his Contemporaries with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48185:51"/>as well atteſting, what he was, as Prophecies or Miracles could do; and, to teach Man, how much he valu'd Him above thoſe Creatures, that man makes his Idols, he often altered and ſuſpended the Courſe of Nature, for mans Inſtruction, or his Relief, and revers'd the Laws, eſtabliſh'd in the Univerſe, to engage Men to obey thoſe of God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12:24.</note> By doing miracles ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and great, that the Jews Unbelief may be almoſt counted one. Yet were thoſe wonders wrought for a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that aſcrib'd them to the Devil,
<note place="margin">Mar. 3.12.</note> &amp; Return'd him with ſo unexampled an Ingratitude, that 'tis not the Leaſt of his wonders that he would vouchſafe to work Any of them for ſuch blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wretches: who were indeed, as ſome of the latter Jews have too truly ſtyl'd themſelves, in relation to their fathers, <hi>Chometz ben ya yin,</hi> Vinegar the Child of Wine, a moſt degenerate Off-ſpring of Holy Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours. He ſuffered ſo much for them, that made him do ſo, that he ſuffered the addition of Miſery of being thought to ſuffer Deſervedly, <hi>and he was numbred with the Tranſgreſſors.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.12.</note> And
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48185:51"/>though he Liv'd as much a Miracle as any he Did, yet did his condition ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times appear ſo Deſpicable and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn, that men could not know his Deity, but by his Goodneſs, which was too Infinite not to be long Incommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably to God. And though 'twere once a ſaying of our Saviour's, <hi>Greater Love hath no man than this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15.13</note> 
               <hi>that a man lay down his life for his Friends;</hi> Yet is not, what is ſaid of the Love here mention'd, to be underſtood of Love Indefinitely or generally conſidered, but onely of the ſingle Acts or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of a mans love to his friends Compar'd betwixt themſelves. And ſo the alleaged paſſage ſeems to mean but this, that among the ſingle Acts of kindneſſe to a mans friends, there is not any One more highly expreſſive of a reall and ſincere Love, than to part with ones Life for their ſakes. This Text therefore would not be indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely applyed to the affection of Love it ſelfe, as if it could not poſſibly be greater then is requiſite to make a man Content or Willing to dye for his friends; for he that ſacrifices beſides his Life, his Fortune alſo, his Children &amp; his Reputation, does thereby expreſs
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48185:52"/>more Love to them than he could do by parting with his Life only for them, And he that is forward to dye for thoſe that Hate him, or, at leaſt, know him not; diſcloſes a more plentifull and exuberant Stock of Love, then he that does the ſame kindneſſe, but for thoſe that Love him. And thus our Saviour would be underſtood, unleſſe we would ſay, that he Out-practiſ'd what he Taught: for, he came to lay down His life ev'n for his Enemies, and (like the kind Balſome Tree, whoſe healing-wounds weep Soveraigne Balm to Cure thoſe that made them) he refus'd not to Dye for thoſe that Kill'd him, and Shed his bloud for ſome of them that Spilt it. And ſo little was his injur'd Love to the ungrateful World diſcouraged or impair'd by the ſavage Entertainment, he met with in it, that, after he had ſuffer'd from wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched men, for whoſe ſakes he left Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to become capable of ſuffering ſuch barbarous Indignities, as might have made bare Puniſhments appear Mercy, and ev'n Cruelty it ſelf ſeem no more than Juſtice; when I ſay, to hope for ſo much as his Pardon were Preſumption; he was pleas'd to Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48185:52"/>Confidence of no leſs than his Love, A vertue. Nor think it, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to our preſent Theme, that I inſiſt ſo much on what Chriſt has Done and Suffer'd for us, ſince he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf informes us;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See alſo</hi> Joh. 14. v. 9, 10, 11.</note> that He and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are one. And ſome of the Texts already mention'd have taught us, that 'twas an effect alſo of God's love to the World,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.16.</note> That <hi>He gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son to Redeem</hi> it; and,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> That <hi>God commendeth his Love towards us in that, while we were yet Sinners, Christ dyed for us.</hi> Wherefore I ſhall without Scruple proceed to obſerve to you, That ſo free is Chriſt's Dilection, that the grand condition of our Felicity is our Belief, that he is diſpos'd to make us Happy on Tearms, not onely ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to him, but ſo Advantagious to us, that, I was about to ſay, That poſſibly Faith it ſelf would ſcarce be exacted, as Requiſite to our happineſſe, but that the Condition does increaſe the Benefit, by vouchſafing us bold and early Anticipations of it: For,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1</note> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> being (as the Apoſtle tearms it) <hi>the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> (or, conviction) <hi>of things not ſeen,</hi> wafts our Joys to this ſide of the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48185:53"/>Grave, bows Heaven down to us, till our freed Spirits can ſoar up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and does us ſuch a ſervice, as the Jewiſh Spies did to their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<note place="margin">Numb. 13 23, 27.</note> by bringing them over, to this ſide <hi>Jordan</hi> into the Wilderneſſe, ſome of the pleaſant and delicious Fruits of the bleſt Land of Promiſe. I ſaid, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that Faith was the grand Condition required, in God's free Grant of Eternall Life. Not that I would aſcribe any thing to a Lazy, Speculative, &amp; Barren Faith, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to that lively and active one, which is called by the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Faith operating by Love;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2.26.</note> ſince I am informed by <hi>St. James,</hi> that the Divorce of Faith and Works is as Deſtructive to Religion, as that of Soul and Body is to Life: But that I was willing to mind you, that though true Faith (which cries like <hi>Rachel, Give me children or elſe I die</hi>) be ever the pregnant Mother of good Works;
<note place="margin">Gen. 30.</note> yet are not thoſe Works the Cauſe, but the Effects and Signes of God's firſt Love to us, (however afterwards the Children may Nurſe their Parents.) As, though the Needle's pointing, at the Poles be, by being an Effect, an
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48185:53"/>Argument of its having been Invigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the Loadſtone, or received Influence from ſome other Magnetick Body; yet is not that Reſpect unto the North the Cauſe, but the Operation of the Iron's being drawn by the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive Minerall. <hi>Thou art good,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.68.</note> and doſt good,</hi> ſaies the Pſalmiſt to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. The Greatneſſe of his Goodneſſe is that which makes it Ours; nor doth He do us good, becauſe that We are good, but becauſe He is liberally ſo; as the Sun ſhines on Dunghills, not out of any Invitation his beams find there, but becauſe it is his Nature, to be diffuſive of his Light; yet with this difference, that whereas the Sun's Bounty, by being rather an Advantage to us than a Favour, deſerves our Joy, and not our Thanks, becauſe his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits are made deſignleſly, and without any particular intention of addreſſe, (by ſuch a bare Neceſſity of Nature, as that which makes Springs flow out into Streams, when their Beds are too narrow to contain the renewed water, that doth inceſſantly ſwell the exuberant Sources:) God, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for being Neceſſarily kind, is not leſſe Freely or Obligeingly ſo, to you
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48185:54"/>or me; for, though ſome kind of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municativeneſſe be Eſſentiall to his Goodneſs, yet his Extenſion of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Himſelf, and his Vouchſafeing it to this or that particular Perſon, are pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Arbitrary. To omit his Love to the numberleſſe Elect Angells; the ſtrict Relations betwixt the perſons of the Bleſſed Trinity, ſupplying God with internall Objects, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd his Kindneſſe before the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and Himſelf being able to allow his Goodneſſe the Extent of Infinity for its Diffuſion. But (having glanc'd at this onely by the By) we may yet further admiringly obſerve, That, whereas men uſually give freelieſt, where they have not given before, and make it both the Motive and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of their deſiſtance from Giving any more, That they have Given alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: Gods bounty hath a very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Method; for he uſes to give, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he Hath given, and, that he May give. Conſonantly to which, when the revolting <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had broken the Contents, whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was bringing them the Tables of the LAVV; and had thereby provok'd the Incenſ'd Given of it, to thoughts of a ſudden Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48185:54"/>of ſo ingratefull and rebellious a People, we may obſerve, That, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God, as unwilling to remember his former Goodneſſe to them, ſpeaking to <hi>Moſes,</hi> calls them, <hi>Thy People which thou broughtest out of the land of Egypt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.7.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> on the other ſide, to engage God to the new Mercy of a Pardon, repreſents to God his former Mercy to them, and calls them <hi>God's People,</hi> which <hi>he brought forth out of the land of Egypt, with great power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and a mighty hand.</hi> And ſo conſpicuous in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Son was this Property of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, that when ſick <hi>Lazarus's</hi> Siſters implored his Reſcue for their exſpiring Brother, the Motive they imploy, and which Proſpered their addreſſes, was, <hi>Lord, behold,</hi> (not,
<note place="margin">Joh. 11.3:</note> he who loveth thee, but) <hi>he whom thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, is ſick.</hi> And as he takes the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements of his Bounty from Himſelf; ſo do his former Favours both invite and give rates to his ſucceeding Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. And there is reaſon for it: for his pure love being all the Merit, by which Man can pretend to the Effects of his Bounty; it is but juſt, that the degree of his Love ſhould proportion thoſe Favours, which 'tis our onely
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48185:55"/>Title to; and that God's Liberality ſhould as well afford Meaſures as Motives to it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Nor is Gods love leſſe Diſ-intereſs'd,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>14</label> than Free. His grand Deſigne upon us, is but to make us Inſtruments and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of His Glory, and to bring us to everlaſting Happineſſe, by a Way that does as well elevate and dignifie our Nature; as the Condition, reſerv'd for us, will. His Method of ſaving us, if but comply'd with, does here, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks,
<note place="margin">Col 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>fit us for the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi> We being made (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>Partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>having eſcap'd the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption that is in the world through Lust;</hi> So that theſe things, wherein the nobleſt of the Philoſophers plac'd their Faelicity, ſerve but to Qualifie and Prepare Chriſtians for that Higher Bleſſedneſſe, that is reſerv'd by God for thoſe that love Him; and cannot, but be heighten'd and endear'd by the Value, which Graces and Vertues had given men on Earth for ſuch a Noble and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall kind of Happineſſe, as is appor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to them in Heaven. What ends can he have upon us, whoſe Goodneſſe and his Bleſſedneſſe are both Infinite?
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48185:55"/>He was unconceivably Happy (in his own Self-ſufficiency) before the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had a Being; and ſure that felicity that needed not Themſelves to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, needs nothing, that they can Do. Nor was it his Indigence, that forc't him to make the World, thereby to make new Acquiſitions, but his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that preſt him to manifeſt, and to impart his Glory; and the goods, which he ſo over-flowingly abounds with. Witneſs his Suſpenſion of the World's Creation, which certainly had had an earlier Date; were the Deity capable of Want, and the Creatures of Supply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> ſtyles God,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.11.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we tranſlate, <hi>The Beſſed God,</hi> but may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more properly be rendred, <hi>The hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py God:</hi> and elſe-where in the ſame Epiſtle, he truly cals him, <hi>The Happy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> as well as <hi>Onely Potentate. God</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>That made the World and all Things therein,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 27.24 25, &amp; 28.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing that He is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwelleth not &amp;c. As though He needed any thing, ſeeing that He giveth to all, Life and Breath, and all Things.</hi> And, <hi>In Him, we live, and move, and have our being.</hi> And indeed, ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in the mind of a mere Man, that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48185:56"/>does but Conſider and Underſtand the Import of his owne Notions, is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of Gods Happineſſe, to that of His Beeing, that I remember the Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean, <hi>Lucretius</hi> himſelfe, ev'n in that impious paſſage, where he denies di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence; and in a ſeeming, but injurious Complement, would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Eaſing God, Deprive Him of the Government of the World; does yet confeſſe, that the Divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt neceſſarily enjoy a ſupream and endleſſe Tranquillity, adding, (to bring this to our preſent purpoſe) that 'tis,
<q>
                  <hi>— Privata dolore omni, privata periclis; Ipſa ſuis pollens opibus, nihil indiga no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strî.</hi>
               </q> Whereby he acknowledges,
<q>
                  <l>That from all griefs and dangers of them freed,</l>
                  <l>Rich in it ſelfe, it has of us no need.</l>
               </q> Or, if you will have him ſpeak of the gods in the Plurall, like a heathen Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48185:56"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Far above griefs and danger, thoſe bleſt Powers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rich in their Native Goods, need none of ours.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>A much Nobler Poet tells us, That <hi>the Earth is the Lord's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 24.1</note> 
               <hi>and the fullneſſe thereof, the World, and they that dwel therein;</hi> Agreeably whereunto,
<note place="margin">Prov. 26.10.</note> that <hi>Great God that formed all things,</hi> (as, in our Tranſlation the Scripture calls him) ſayes in one of the Pſalms, <hi>If I were hungry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 50.12.</note> 
               <hi>I would not tell thee, for the World is mine, and the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.</hi> His Ubiquity excludes all wiſhes of Remoove, by making his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence uncapable of Excluſion; For Whither ſhould he deſire to Tranſport himſelfe, that is Every where, and can wiſh himſelfe in no place, where he is not already? His Sufficiency is ſuch, that he can ſee no goods, but what he Gives, or Hath (or rather both beſtowes and poſſeſſes) his Plenty being ſo unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted a ſpring of goods, that his libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality does leſſe impoveriſh God, than the Suns light does him; or imparted knowledg, impairs the Teacher's ſtock. And therefore, though St. <hi>James</hi> do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry juſtly call God, <hi>That Father of Lights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.17.</note> who is the beſtower of every good and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48185:57"/>every perfect Gift;
<note place="margin">Jam. 2.23.</note> yet the <hi>Friend of God,</hi> (as the Scripture calls <hi>Abraham</hi>) and that Royall Prieſt,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note> (whom the Writer to the Hebrewes teaches us to have been ſo illuſtrious a Type of Him, whom he calls <hi>The high Prieſt of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi>) do both of them in the ſame Chapter ſtyle him <hi>the Poſſeſſour of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.1.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.18, 22.</note> No, no, God needs not beg From, or covet, In the Creatures ſhallow ſtreams, thoſe goods, of which he not onely Hath, but Is the Source. Our greateſt Services to our Creator muſt be to Diſcharge our ſelves, not to Advantage him, nor as thinking to adde any thing to a Felicity, which were not Infinite, could it admit Encreaſe; Our higheſt Performances, though they be Dues, amount not unto Tributes, but are rather like thoſe pepper Corns of Rent, which Free-holders pay, not with hope or with intent to enrich their Land-lord, but to acknowledge, that they hold all from him. When we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Sun, our Seeing of his light doth not Increaſe it, it makes it not Greater, but only it makes it Ours; and when we turn away or ſhut our eyes, that glorious Planet ſuffers no Eclipſe, and is not at all darkn'd or impair'd,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48185:57"/>nor doth He thereby loſe his light, but We: The Eaſineſs of the application requires, and excuſes its Omiſſion. <hi>If thou ſinneſt</hi> (ſayes <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Job) what doeſt thou againſt him? if thou be righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 35.6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>what giveſt thou him? or what receiveth he of thine hand? Thy wickedneſſe may hurt a man, as thou art, and thy righteouſneſſe may profit the Son of man.</hi> In effect, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked's ſpite againſt God, is but like a mad mans running his head againſt a wall, that leaves the Wall unſhaken, but daſhes his own Brains out. God <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habits</hi> a Felicity (as well as <hi>Light) inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible</hi> to all inferiour attempts: His ſoveraign Tranquillity is ſo ſublimely plac'd, that 'tis above the reach of all Diſquieting Impreſſions; and, like the Stars, that feel not the diſeaſes, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſpicious Influence produces, He doth not Reſent the Torments, he Inflicts. Gods juſtice is no leſs Eſſentiall to him, then his Mercy; Witneſſe that, (the numbers of the Saints, and the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates conſider'd) thouſands fall Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to the ſeverer Attribute, for one that proves Capable of the milder. He ſaid,
<note place="margin">Exod. 14.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>he would get himſelfe honour upon</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and all his Hoſt;</hi> when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd their ruine in the <hi>Red Sea:</hi> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48185:58"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ex. 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>He hath Triumphed gloriouſly</hi> in effecting it. And in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> he ſayes, <hi>Behold I am againſt thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 28.22.</note> 
               <hi>O Sidon, and I will be glorify'd in the midst of thee, and they ſhall know that I am the Lord, when I ſhall have executed my judgments in her, and ſhall be ſanctify'd in her.</hi> Thus, when a Flaſh of Gods Indignation (kindled by that <hi>ſtrange fire,</hi> they preſum'd to offer before him) had blaſted the two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> God is ſaid <hi>To have been ſanctify'd in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>that come nigh him, and to have been glorify'd before all the people;</hi> ſuch eminent and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Inſtances of Severity, manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be ſo Holy in his Laws, and ſo Concern'd for them; That ev'n the Miniſters of his Altars ſhall not violate them with Impunity,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> but find Him (what the Writer to the Hebrewes calls him) <hi>A conſuming fire;</hi> Who will be Glorify'd before all his people, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Obedience of thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him, or by their Deſtruction: So to evidence, that God can derive Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as well from the Exerciſe of his provoked Juſtice, as from that of his for ward Mercy; The ſacred Orator uſes this remarkable <hi>Antanaclaſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 18.63.</note> 
               <hi>And it ſhal come to paſſe, that as the Lord rejoyced over
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48185:58"/>you to do you good, and multiply you; ſo will the Lord rejoyce over you to deſtroy you, and bring you to nought.</hi> Thus, though it be truly ſaid of God by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that <hi>he doth not afflict willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.33</note> 
               <hi>nor grieve the children of men:</hi> And therefore the determined Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Land, which our Bibles Engliſh, <hi>God's work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.21.</note> 
               <hi>his ſtrange work;</hi> other Tranſlators render, <hi>Opus alienum ſaum:</hi> Yet when the Sins of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible offenders are grown to that provoking Heighth, that his Mercy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes no more, to avert or ſuſpend the inflictions of his Juſtice; then how much he can ſatisfie himſelf in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying thoſe, that would not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, may be gueſs'd at by that formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Expreſſion in <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving foretold what havock the Sword, the Famine, and the Peſtilence ſhould make, amongſt the intractable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed Iſraelites, he adds, (as a kind of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Thus ſhall mine anger be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>and I will cauſe my fury to reſt upon them, and I will be comforted.</hi> The Houlings of the Damned as wel ſound forth his praiſes, as do the Hallelujahs of the Saints; they both do ſing to him an everlaſting Canticle of praiſe; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48185:59"/>in this great Conſort of his whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Intelligent Creation, the deſignleſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſpiring Voices are as Differing, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Conditions of the reſpective Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Hell's darkneſſe doth as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to God's Glory, as Heaven's Eternall Splendour: As Shadows, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly plac'd, do no leſſe praiſe the Painter, than do the livelier and brighter Colours. And as when the Earth doth ſend black, noiſome, and ſulphureous Exhalations up toward the Sky; alas, they reach not Heaven nor diſcompoſe the Spheres; but all the Storms and Thunders they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, fall on that Globe they came from, and there do all their miſchief<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So, the wicked may Wrong God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, yet do they really Harm but themſelves, by all their greateſt ſins, which trouble him chiefly, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neceſſitate Him to puniſh them: for the tranſgreſſions, that do moſt Provoke God, do him not the leaſt harm. An impious perſon may (as <hi>Elihu</hi> lately inform'd us) hurt a man, as himſelf is; not that ſupreamly bleſſed Deity: the Reſult of whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Perfections is a reſembling Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, which is as inſeparable from
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48185:59"/>Him, as his Eſſence. Our offences may derogate from his Acceſſionall Glory, not from his Eſſentiall Faelicity; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt deſperate Sinners, by their greateſt Crimes, can but Change the Attribute they ſhould bring honour to, and but oppoſe the glorifying of his Goodneſſe, to occaſion the glorifying of his Juſtice; Since he will be infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly glorify'd, ſoon or late, either by mens actions, or their ſufferings; by their Practice of Duties, or Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Sinne. Thus you ſee, how little God is beholden to you for your declining Hell: Nor will the ſcore be very much increaſ'd by your addreſſes and attempts for Heaven. <hi>Can a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 22.2, 3.</note> (ſayes <hi>Eliphaz) be profitable unto God, as he that is wiſe may be profitable unto himſelfe? Is it any pleaſure to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty that thou art righteous? or, is it gain unto him that thou makeſt thy wayes perfect?</hi> Congruouſly to which ſenſe the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſayes,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>My Goodneſſe extendeth not to Thee;</hi> The fire that we kindle on God's altars, heats and enlightens Us, but warms not Heaven at ſo diſtant a remove, nor is wanted in the Sun's reſidence. We have all the Redolence of the Perfumes and Incenſe, we burn
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48185:60"/>upon his Altars; the Smoak doth Vaniſh ere it can reach the Sky, and whilſt tis undiſperſt, but cloud's, and but Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcures it: Alas, our Beſt Performances are as uſeleſſe Services to God, as the Heir's bringing Wax to his departing Father is to him; which addes not any thing to the rich mans ſtore, and is by him deſir'd and accepted, onely to Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away a Fortune to his Sonne. Though therefore it be true, that God is Pleaſ'd with our performances, yet is that Welcome he vouchſafes to give them, ſo far from enabling us by them, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite his Love, that it encreaſes the Unrequitedneſſe of it; Since he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with them, as they afford him juſt Riſes to reward them. How far from Mercenary is then Gods Bounty? ſince he accepts our Acknowledgments of his former bleſſings, (chiefly), to make them Opportunities of conferring freſh ones; as good old <hi>Iſaac</hi> deſir'd his Sons veniſon, that from the relliſhing of that ſavory meat, he might take an opportunity to bleſſe him.</p>
            <p>And,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>15</label> to diſcover how diſintereſs'd God's Favours are, let us further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how little they are requitable: for we can give Him nothing, but his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:48185:60"/>owne, (nor, Heaven knows, all that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther); and both the Will and Power to ſerve Him are his, upon ſo juſt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scores, that we are unable to Retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, unleſſe we do Reſtore; and all the Duties we can pay our Maker, are leſſe properly Requitals than Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When <hi>David</hi> and his Officers had offer'd towards the Structure of that Magnificent Temple, which they ſeem'd Ambitious to make a Manſion inferiour to Heaven onely; the King himſelf gave three thouſand Talents of Gold, and ſeven of refin'd Silver: and the Heads of the People, five Thouſand Talents, (beſides Ten Thouſand Drachms of Gold) ten Thouſand Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of Silver, eighteen thouſand of Braſſe, and a hundred thouſand of Iron, (a Treaſure, of which, I ſcarce remember to have read the like in any Hiſtory); beſides a number of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pretious Stones, capable of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhing the very <hi>Indies:</hi> They per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fum'd this noble and unequal'd Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with a ſolemn Confeſſion, which perhaps, in God's eſteem, was much more pretious than It: <hi>Thine, O Lord,</hi> (ſaies the Royall Prophet in the name of all) <hi>is the greatneſſe, and the power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chro 29.11, 1 13, 14, 1 16</note>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:48185:61"/>
               <hi>and the glory, and the victory, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; for all that is in heaven and in earth is thine. Thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted as head above all. Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reigneſt over all. And in thine hand is power and might, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give ſtrength unto all. Now therefore, our God, we thank thee, and praiſe thy glorious Name. But who am I? and what is my people, that we ſhould be able to offer ſo willingly after this ſort? For all things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee. For we are ſtrangers before thee, and ſoiourners, as were all our fathers. Our daies on earth are as a ſhadow, and there is none abiding. O Lord our God, all this ſtore, that we have prepared to build thee an houſe, for thy holy name, commeth of thine hand, and is all thine own.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>Who</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle, in a Queſtion that imports its own Negative) <hi>hath firſt given to him, and it ſhall be recompenced to him again? For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things:</hi> Nay, even our Love it ſelf, (that poor-man's Surety and Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, that doth pay all his Debts, by ſupplying him with the Prerogative to Coyne his Deſires and Wiſhes of an
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48185:61"/>Arbitrary value) is here unable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our Debts: our Love is too much the Effect, to be capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Recompence of God's. And ſurely,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.10.</note> the Divine Amoriſt had cauſe to ſay, that <hi>herein is love, not that we lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God, but that he loved us.</hi> And, as the ſame Apoſtle elſewhere ſpeaks, <hi>We love him, becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> If,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.19.</note> in effect, we look upon the unworthy Conteſt, betwixt God's Mercies, and moſt men's Ingratitude, and but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the ſmall Return of Love, that the greateſt Disburſments of His, do uſually bring home; we cannot but acknowledge, (as <hi>David,</hi> in the lately mentioned Scripture, did) that our loving God for his Favours, is one of the greateſt Favours that we love him for; ſo Unrequitable is God's love and ſo Inſolvent are we, that that love vaſtly improves the Benefit; by which alone we might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſome ability of Retribution; And ſo unlimited is this Impotence of ours to recompence or repay God's Dilection, that it extends to, and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters our very Wiſhes. For God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys an Affluence of Felicity, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and entire, that even our Wiſhes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48185:62"/>can aime at nothing for him Worthy of him, unleſſe inſtructed by what he already actually Poſſeſſes. And the Senſe of this ſame very Impotence, to ſome of the greateſt Proficients in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphick Love,</hi> appears not the leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie Property of it. It grieves us ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, to ſee our ſelves reduc'd to be onely Paſſive, and Receivers in this Commerce. We would fain contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Something, and cannot alwaies refrain from devoting our Wiſhes to encreaſe His Happineſſe, to whom we owe all Ours. And ſome Holy Perſons (particularly St. <hi>Austind</hi>) have by the Exuberance of their Gratitude and Devotion, been tranſported to make Wiſhes, and uſe Expreſſions, wherein their Affections had a greater ſhare than their Reaſon, and which argued them much better to apprehend, How much God deſerv'd of them, than How little he needed them But, upon ſecond thoughts, we ſhall find, that the cauſe of our Grief ought to turn it into our Joy, ſince the Deſires we would frame, aiming at God's being infinitely happy, are all Fulfilled before they are Conceived, and that in the moſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious and Nobleſt way: For
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48185:62"/>could God's happineſſe admit Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by our accompliſht Wiſhes, there were then a poſſibility of his Wanting ſomething to render it Compleat. And ſure, 'Tis a more Supream felicity, to be by Nature tranſcendently above All encreaſe of Bleſſedneſſe, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Greateſt that men can wiſh.</p>
            <p>To proceed now to the Conſtancy of Gods Love:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>16</label> we cannot entertaine of God any Apprehenſions, not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unworthy of Him and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Injurious to him, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, That to think that he can be Inconſtant, is as great a Crime as 'twere a Miſery to find him ſo; his Love is like his Eſſence, immutably Eternall, reaching from Everlaſting to Everlaſting; it preceded the Nativity of Time, and will ſurvive its utmoſt Period and obſequies. <hi>Having loved his own which were in the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>he loved them unto the end,</hi> ſayes the Evangeliſt: and when St. <hi>James</hi> had told us, That <hi>every good gift and every perfect gift is from above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>and commeth down from the Father of Lights,</hi> he adds (to compleat our Conſolation) <hi>with whom is no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riableneſſe neither ſhadow of turning. Of his own Will begat he us of the word of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48185:63"/>Truth;</hi> and, in effect, ſince God takes the Motives of his Love to us from Himſelf, not from Us, the unchangable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Nature ſeems ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gly to inferre that of his Charity and our Happineſſe in it. For, <hi>I am the Lord, I change not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>therefore ye ſons of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob are not conſumed,</hi> ſayes God by the laſt of his prophets. And in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ah</hi> he tells his people, <hi>I have lov'd thee with an everlaſting Love:</hi> And what God once ſaid to the generous <hi>Joſuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will never leave thee nor forſake thee,</hi> is by the Writer to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to believers in generall:
<note place="margin">Heb 13.5</note> for <hi>the gifts and calling of God</hi> (ſayes the ſame Author elſewhere) <hi>are without repentance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> Nor do thoſe Croſſes that ſeem due to his Anger, deſtroy the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability of his Love, ſince ev'n that Anger is an Effect of it, proceeding from a Fatherly Impatience of ſeeing a Spot unwip'd off in the Face, he loves too well to ſuffer a blemiſh in it; and from a Deſire to ſee his Child an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject fit for a larger Meaſure of his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; as when we beat the duſt out of a Suite we fancie, we ſtrike not out of Anger, but onely to remove that which doth ſully it, and hinder us to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48185:63"/>take that delight in it, which our fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would be pleaſ'd with a juſt Cauſe to find. <hi>As many as I love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and chaſten,</hi> (ſayes our Saviour) And, <hi>I know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.75.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſayes the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>that thy Judgments are right, and that thou in faithfulneſſe hath afflicted me.</hi> The Furnace of Affliction being meant but to Refine us from our earthly droſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and Soften us for the Impreſſion of Gods own Stamp and Image. The great and mercifull Architect of his Church (whom not onely the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have ſtyl'd, but the Scripture it ſelf calls,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.10.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an artiſt or Artificer) imploys not on us the Hammer, and the Chizzell, with an intent to Wound or Mangle us, but onely to Square and faſhion our hard and ſtubborn Hearts into ſuch living Stones,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5.</note> as may both Grace and Strengthen his heavenly Structure. Nor is God only thus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to his Love, but to his Lovelineſſe. Our female Beauties are uſually as fickle in their Faces as their Minds, and more certainly in the former: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though Caſualties ſhould ſpare them, Age brings in a neceſſity of a Change, nay, a Decay, leaving our doters upon Red and White, inceſſantly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48185:64"/>perplext, by the incertainty both of the Continuance of their Miſtriſſe's Kindneſſe, and of the laſting of her Beauty (both which are neceſſary to the <hi>Amoriſt's</hi> Joys and quiet): for, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when the Miſtreſſe's humour doth not change ſo much, as to prove guilty of the fault of Inconſtancy, her face alters enough to make her Lovers wiſh Inconſtancy no fault; Or, that ſhe had committed it, that her Fickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might afford them the Excuſe of Imitation or Revenge: But in Devotion, we are equally ſecure from both theſe Dangers. Since God nor doth deſiſt from bleſſing us with his Love, nor ceaſes ever from deſerving the Heighth of ours: Nor is he onely conſtant in making us the Objects of His Love, but alſo in bending and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us to make him the Object of Ours: ſo that he not only perſiſts in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us both the Offer and the Value of his Love, but perſeveres to give us a receptive Diſpoſition to Welcome it to us, and reflect it up to Him. The want of this laſt mercy loſt <hi>Adam</hi> Paradiſe and Satan, Heaven; there being to the Objects, that muſt Secure our love, ſuch a Nature requiſite in reference to our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48185:64"/>Affections; as Philoſophers are pleaſ'd to aſcribe to the world's Center in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Heavy bodyes, which, they teach us, that Magnetick poynt has the double Faculty not only to Draw thither, but to Keep there: for ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward and Croſſegrain'd are we, in poynt of our own Good, and ſo unfit to procure, and ready to deſert, our own Felicity; that neither its Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie is a ſufficient Motive to carry our addreſſes to it, nor its poſſeſſion a competent Tye, to intercept in us all deſigns of Revolts and Divorces: but we muſt be uſed as peeviſh Children are, who (on the one ſide) when their mouths are out of taſte, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take what is neceſſary for them, muſt have it not only Offer'd them, but Forc'd upon them, and be (as it were) Made to receive it; and who (on the other ſide) muſt be reſtrain'd from gadding, when the Beauty of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they live in, cannot invite their ſtay, but they would gladly leave the proudeſt Pallaces, Architecture can boaſt, to Runne into the Street and Dabble in the Kennel: All theſe three properties of Divine Conſtancy are not ill ſhadow'd in the operations of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48185:65"/>the Load-ſtone, a Minerall, in which I have made too many Experiments, not to be by you allow'd to make ſome Compariſons to it. For, firſt, it never forſakes its Inclinations for the Steel: next, being united to it, it retains ſo conſtantly its Attractive qualities, that it gives not the Needle any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of deſerting it: and thirdly, it doth never rightly touch the amorous Steel, without leaving an Impreſſion, which ever after diſpoſes it to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to that Magnetick Poſture, which beſt fits it to receive freſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences. To which, let me add this other reſemblance, betwixt God's work on Us, and the Load-ſtone's on the Iron; that the Kind Stone attracts a Needle to it, not to Advantage it ſelf by that Union, but to Impart its Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to what it draws. Beſides, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Rivalls, thoſe frequent Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iners of other Lovers happineſſe, can threaten nothing of formidable to yours: For Abſence (which ſo divorces us from that which animates us, that Lovers do not ſo improperly ſtyle it Death, if Death be but the Separation of Soul and Body) by God's Ubiquity we are ſecured from; He is ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48185:65"/>With us; or rather In us. You that not long ſince ſo highly valu'd the Opportunities of converſing with your Miſtriſs for ſome few Moments, ſhall here find your Priviledges im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to a Permiſſion (nay, an Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) of entertaining the Object of your Love at all times; no hour ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders your viſits Unſeaſonable, nor no length Tedious: he is rather welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to God, that comes to him Ofteneſt and ſtays with him Longeſt. What fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were vouchſaf'd to that antient Propheteſſe (who was likewiſe one of the firſt Evangeliſts) who for many years <hi>departed not from the Temple; but ſerved God with Fastings and Prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 2.37. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Night and Day,</hi> the beginning of St. <hi>Luke's</hi> Goſpell may inform you. The <hi>midnight-Hymns</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> did not only not diſturb or Offend him they praiſ'd,
<note place="margin">Act. 16.25 26, &amp;c.</note> but procur'd the viſit of an Angell to bring them miraculous and unexpected Liberty, as a proofe of the Acceptableneſſe of their not-Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Devotions,
<note place="margin">Gen. 5. 22, 23, 24.</note> When <hi>Enoch had wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God</hi> as many years as the year has dayes, God was ſo farre from being Importun'd or Tir'd by that laſting aſſiduity, that vouchſafing him an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exampled
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48185:66"/>exampled Exemption from death, he was pleaſ'd by a new and nearer Cut to Heaven, to admit him to a yet Cloſer, more Immediate, and more Undiſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Communion with himſelf. And when <hi>Moſes</hi> had ſpent no leſſe than <hi>forty dayes and forty nights</hi> in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (if I may uſe ſo Familiar a term) with God in the Mount,
<note place="margin">Exod. 34.30.</note> he brought down thence inſtead of a Pennance for his Importunity, ſo ſignall and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant a Teſtimony of Gods peculiar Favour, that his dazl'd Country-men were as much Diſabled, as Invited to gaze on an Object of ſo much wonder. And then, How proud doe we ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lovers of their Sufferings; when ſhe but Knows of them, for whom they are endured? But in <hi>Seraphick Love,</hi> there is not the leaſt good Wiſh or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateſt Suffering; nay, not a whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Sigh, or cloſer Thought, that ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Groans or Aſpires in the Amorous Soul, but He both ſees and heares, that Puts his Servant's <hi>teares into his Bottle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 36.8.</note> ſweetning and recompencing the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Misfortunes that his Love oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, with ſuch Support and Joyes, as hinder us to feel them; and make them deſerve a contrary name. Each
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48185:66"/>amorous Soul may ſay to God with <hi>David: Thou knoweſt my down-ſitting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 139.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and my up-riſing, thou underſtandeſt my thoughts afar off, thou compaſſeſt my path, and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my wayes.</hi> And Chriſt alſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has ſo attentive an Eye upon the Amorous Soul, that he is held forth, in the Apocalypſe, as telling the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy works, and tribulation, and poverty;</hi> And <hi>ſaying to the Angell of the</hi> Church of <hi>Pergamus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy works and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satans ſeat is, and thou holdeſt faſt my name, and haſt not denied my Faith even in thoſe dayes, wherein Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas was my Faithfull Martyr who was ſlain among you, where Satan dwelleth.</hi> So that no endearing Circumſtance of our Love, ſcapes unobſerv'd by Him, who has done and ſuffered ſo much to engage us to it. God remembers not our Endeavours to ſerve Him, the leſſe, for Our having forgotten them.
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.37, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>When ſaw we thee any way diſtreſſed, and relieved thee?</hi> will be the Queſtion of thoſe, to whom Heaven it ſelf will be at the laſt Day awarded, as having miniſtred to their Redeemer. Thoſe, that in Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate times, ſuch as ours, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:48185:67"/>did, like <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> mourn for their Sins, that mourned not for their own, and condol'd among themſelves, the Spreading Wickedneſſe of the times they liv'd in, though probably the dangers, threatned them by the very Sinfulneſſe they deplor'd, made them affect ſuch Privacyes in their Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, as freed them from the Thoughts of being over-heard; yet the Scripture informs us, (and 'tis a Comfortable, as well as Memorable Paſſage) that <hi>the Lord hearkened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal 3.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his name. Then ſhall he return, and diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not. I know,</hi> ſays Chriſt (not only to the Angell of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> but to each true ſufferer for Him) <hi>thy works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>and tribulation, and poverty: Fear none of theſe things, that thou ſhalt ſuffer: Be thou faithfull unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life.</hi> God is often pleas'd to accept thoſe good thoughts and Intentions of his Servants, which never arrive at actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Performances, Though <hi>David</hi> built not the Temple he deſign'd, yet his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48185:67"/>Son, that did it, informs us, that God ſaid unto him,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>Foraſmuch as it was in thine heart to build an houſe for my Name; Thou didſt well in that it was in thine heart,</hi> &amp;c. And 'tis the Epithet our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gives God;
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Your Father which ſeeth in ſecret,</hi> &amp;c. Nor need we fear, our Rivalls ſhould ſupplant us, ſince we can have none in Devotion, whoſe Prayer and Endeavour it is not, that God would love us more. For his Love to you being (as the chiefeſt Merit) the ſtrongeſt Motive and Title unto theirs, they cannot but Wiſh him well whom God doth Love ſo; and cannot Wiſh him better, then by imploring for him, freſh Additions both of that Love of God, and gratefull Diſpoſitions to return it. Our Saviours aſſures us, that <hi>there is Joy in the Preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 15.7, 10.</note> 
               <hi>that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</hi> And the ſole Hymne (except a viſionary one) I find recorded of the Coeleſtiall Quire,
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.13, 14.</note> was ſung for a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to mankind, wherein (for ought I know) their Love and Sympathy alone concern'd them:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>For unto us</hi> (men) <hi>the Child is born, and unto us the Son is given.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.16</note> 
               <hi>Who took not upon him the nature of Angells, but the ſeed of Abraham.</hi> So
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48185:68"/>Noble and ſo diſ-intereſs'd, doth Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Love make ours, that there is nothing beſides the Object of that Love, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we love more, then our Concurrents i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it; perhaps out of a Gratitude to their aſſiſting us, to pay a Debt (of Love and Praiſe) for which (alas!) we find ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſingle ſelves but too Inſolvent.</p>
            <p>Perhaps I need not mind you,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>17</label>
               <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi> that divers Paſſages of the fore going Diſcourſe, ſuppoſe the truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Their Doctrine, who aſcribe to God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> relation to every man, an Eternall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable and Inconditionate Decre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Election, or Reprobation; Yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Controverſies betwixt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Praedeſtination and the cohaerent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, it were Improper to give you here my ſenſe: The Godly of both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are perhaps otherwiſe look't on b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, then by one another, as conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which of Gods Attributes ſhould be moſt Reſpected, the one ſeeming t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Affirm irreſpective Decrees, to magnifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Goodneſſe; and the other to Den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them but to Secure the credit of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Juſtice. And ev'n in Honouring the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attribute his Goodneſſe, theſe Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſeem Rivalls, the one party ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48185:68"/>it beſt Celebrated by believing it ſo Irreſiſtible, that to whom ſoever 'tis intended, he Cannot but be happy; and the other thinking it moſt Extoll'd by being believ'd ſo Univerſul, that it will make Every man happy, if he pleaſes: the one party electing to honour Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, by aſſigning it (as to men) an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitedly-vaſt Extent; as the other does, by aſcribing it an infallibly-victorious Degree. But though my haſte, and the nature of my Theme make me decline the Controverſies about Praedeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet ſince the Doctrine, that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines it, is not onely by almoſt all the reſt of Mankind, but by the reſt of the Proteſtant Churches themſelves, the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and divers learned Divines of the Church of England, not onely Rejected, but Deteſted as little leſs, than Blaſphemous, (as indeed they, that judg it an Error, cannot but be tempted to think it a Dangerous one, and of very pernicious Conſequence, ſo far forth, as its Sequels are permitted to have Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on mens Practice) I think it not amiſſe to advertiſe you, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of Praedeſtination is not Neceſſary to Juſtifie the Freeneſſe and the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods Love. For, ſo conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:48185:69"/>and Refulgent a Truth is that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God's being the Author of mans Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, that the diſpute betwixt the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> is not ſo much concerning the Thing, as concerning the Manner of its being proffer'd; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer affirming Grace to be Irreſiſtibly preſented; the latter, though they deny it to be Irrejectable, yet granting, not only that it is altogether Free and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerv'd, but alſo, that the proffer is made both with a Power enabling thoſe, to whom 'tis tender'd, to accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, and with ſuch engaging Invitations that man at his firſt Converſion need contribute nothing to his Faelicity, but the not-wilfully Refuſing it, and may more properly be ſaid to owe it unto God, then the Begger to owe his Almes to his Reliever, though he open his hand to receive it, which he might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to do, if he would have wilfully courted his owne Prejudice; Chriſt paid <hi>a ranſome to redeem us,</hi> 'tis true, and he is therefore call'd, <hi>The Lord that bought us:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> but it was God's free Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, both to provide us That Chriſt, and to accept of That Ranſome, neither of which he was Oblig'd to do; and therefore, the Scripture aſcribes it not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:48185:69"/>to the Juſtice, but to the love of God to the world,
<note place="margin">John 3.16.</note> that <hi>He ſent His only begotten Son to redeem</hi> it: and St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame Text tells us both,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> that <hi>we are Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify'd,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>freely by his Grace,</hi> and yet that it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>through the Redemption,</hi> (purchaſ'd for a Ranſome; the Original word engliſh'd Redemption, relating to the Price, pay'd for the Redeeming of Captives) <hi>that is in Jeſus Christ.</hi> 'Tis confeſt on all hands, that Merit muſt be diſclaim'd, and thoſe that ſeem to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome thing from God as a Due, acknowledge, that if his Promiſe did not, their Actions could not, make it ſo; and that 'tis to his Mercy, they owe the right they have to confide in his Juſtice. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. v. 7, 8.</note> having <hi>fought the good fight, finiſht his Courſe, and kept the Faith,</hi> expected <hi>a Crown of Righteouſneſſe from the Lord,</hi> under the Notion of the Righteous <hi>Judge;</hi> yet tells us that <hi>by grace we are ſav'd, through faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>and that not of our ſelves, it is the Gift of God.</hi> Whoſe Promiſes, now they are made us, allow us indeed to expect Heaven from his Juſtice;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but <hi>the making us thoſe great and precious promiſes,</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> juſtly ſtyles them) muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:48185:70"/>the pure Effect of <hi>his free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved Goodneſſe;</hi> which to believe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, we need but conſider the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion betwixt ſuch a Recompence, as Eternall Glory and the leaſt Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Performances of ours: which, though they Needed not Pardon, could not at leaſt Challenge any Reward, from Him, who, as our Creatour, has ſuch a Right to exact of us what ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he pleaſes, without propoſing us any Recompence, that our exacteſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all his Commands, would yet leave us to confeſſe our ſelves <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> who <hi>have done, but what it was our Duty to do,</hi> and what if we had not done, we had given God, who had the Power, the Right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to puniſh us. And indeed, ſo conſcious are men Generally, (if not Naturally) to their being beholding to God for their Felicity, that even thoſe, that miſtake or oppoſe his way of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them good, will yet be ſure to find out ſome Notion or other, under which they may conceive themſelves God's Debtours for his Bleſſings. That the more ſober ſort of Romiſh Catholicks themſelves, aſcribe not ſo much to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, (properly ſo call'd) nor ſo little to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:48185:70"/>Gods Grace, as the more Quarrelſome Writers of their Party, have given the more eager Diſputants of ours, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to reproach them; were perhaps no difficult task to manifeſt, if my haſte would give me leave. That the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> own the Freeneſſe and Unmeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe of Gods grace, The Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>eſpecially</hi> Chap. 17. Num, 5, 6</note> Confeſsion, and Apology, are very carefull to ſatisfie the World. And ev'n the <hi>Socinians,</hi> (how proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, I determine not) are not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, nor un-induſtriouſly ſollicitous to free their Erroneous Doctrine of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, from the objected guilt of its tendency to draw the Imbracers of it to <hi>Sacrifice to their own Nets,</hi> and thank themſelves for their Faelicity; Which brings into my mind a paſſage, that I lately read in one of the chief modern Up-holders of that Sect, <hi>Schlichtingius,</hi> Who is wont, in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, where his Subject will beare it, to diſcourſe as Fairly and as Rationally as almoſt any Writer, that I have met with of his Perſwaſion; and who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to reconcile <hi>Socinus</hi> his Doctrine with the Freeneſſe of Gods Grace, by Conſiderations, which, not to injure him, I ſhall preſent you with in his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48185:71"/>owne words. — <hi>Ad retundendam verò</hi> (ſayes he, diſputing againſt the Learned <hi>Meiſnerus) arrogantiam justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatorum, &amp; ne dicant ſe meruiſſe Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, non est neceſſe, ſervum in homine arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium inducere; non debet virtus tolli ut tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur arrogantia. Sufficit,</hi> 1. <hi>Quòd nec velle nec perficere poſſint, niſi Deus &amp; voluntatem excitet &amp; vires augeat</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">pag. 97.</note> 
               <hi>Quòd ea, quae divinis adjuti viribus faciunt, nullo modo dignitate &amp; pretio divinae gratiae reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant, ſed infinito intervallo ab eâ abſint.</hi> Nay, though the modern and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Jewes be, upon the Score of being the great Patrons of mans Free-will, not cauſleſly eſteem'd the great Oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Gods Free grace; yet both from their famous Rabbi, and my learned Acquaintance <hi>Menaſſah Ben Iſrael,</hi> and from divers others of their moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Writers, has the truth ſometimes extorted Confeſsions, which though made upon Erroneous grounds, were not very far ſhort of Orthodox. To which purpoſe I remember, that a Jewiſh profeſſour of Hebrew, (who aſſiſted me in my ſtudies of that myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tongue) being, as the reſt of his Nation, an eager and peremptory Champion of Free-will, conceiv'd that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:48185:71"/>even that Liberty, which to us ſeems leaſt to Indebt men to their Creatour, did tranſcendently oblige him unto God. For, one day that we were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately and freely diſcourſing together of matters of Religion, he told me, he thought Men ow'd more to Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then the very Angells do. For, ſaid he, whereas God, without any good work of theirs, but purely out of his Goodneſſe, conferr'd on them that bleſt Condition, they enjoy; by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Man a free Will, by the good Uſe of which he may Glorifie his Maker, when by Abuſing it, 'tis in his power to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour him, he allows man that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Satisfaction, and Priviledge of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operating to his owne Felicity.</p>
            <p>And now,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>18</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> we are arrived at the laſt Property, which qualify's God the fitteſt Object for our Love, which is, the <hi>Advantagiouſnes</hi> of His to us both in the Preſent &amp; the Future Life. And firſt ev'n in this World we owe God no leſſe then All the goods we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, we owe him both What we have and That we are: for we may truly ſay of God with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>It is he, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath made us, and not we our ſelves.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we were not onely in his hands, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:48185:72"/>
               <hi>clay in the Potter's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 64.8.</note> that he might have made us any thing; but we were ſo purely that Negative, from whence we were extracted, that He, (if he had pleaſ'd) for ever might have left us to our firſt Nothing. His Love is the Originall and Fountain-bleſsing; all the reſt are but as Pipes (and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) to convay it, and ſerve but to hand it to us. Your Wit wins you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, Your Induſtry heaps you up Treaſures; be it granted. But who gave you that Wit? and did both Give and Proſper that boaſted Induſtry, Certainly, God as much Gives us all the goods, we Poſſeſſe, as he, that gives a begger a Thouſand Pounds, gives him the Cloaths and Meat and all the Bravery, it helps him to. But, beſides theſe more obvious Preſents of Gods Bounty, we enjoy other Effects of his Goodneſſe, which though by the Cuſtomarineſſe of their being poſſeſſed, they prove leſſe Conſpicuous, than the other; yet grow no leſſe Priz'd, when the Want or Loſs of them, make us ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the true value of them. Had I the leiſure, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> to lead your thoughts with me to the Galleys, and ſhow you there thoſe wretched Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:48185:72"/>that are chain'd to the Oars they tugg at, and though expoſ'd to all the Miſeries and Hardſhips of a Tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sea, have oftentimes cauſe given them by their Barbarous Uſage aſhore, to fear the Ocean leſſe then any Port ſave Death. Could I draw for you the Curtains of ſick and dying men, and open to you that ſad Scene, where ſome pine and languiſh away by Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that deprive them of all the Joyes, Advantages, and (what is more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable) Uſes of life, before they eaſe them of life it ſelfe; others Breathe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Live, perpetually Tormented either with their Diſeaſes or Phyſick to protract a wretched Life, upon tearms that turn it into a Trouble: And others ſtrugling with the rude Pangs of Death, are yet perchance leſſe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Them, then by the ſad Proſpect of their former Life, and the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thoſe Criminall pleaſures, <hi>which yet it perhaps leſſe troubles them, that they muſt now fore-goe, then that they once enjoy'd them.</hi> Should I, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> bring you into Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalls, and ſhow you there the various Shapes of Human Miſery, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:48185:73"/>Souls, narrowly lodg'd (if I may ſo ſpeak) in Synecdochicall bodies, ſee their earthen Cottages moulder away to Duſt; thoſe miſerable perſons by the loſſe of one Limb after another, ſurviving but Part of Themſelves, and living to ſee themſelves Dead and Buri'd by piece-meal. Should I, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> ſhow you all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Companies of Mourners, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt make up Mankind, and diſcloſe to you how copious ſhowers of Tears do almoſt every where water (not to ſay overflow) this vale of Miſeries; You would perchance ſee cauſ to think, that God's Privative may contend with his Poſitive Favours; and that you owe little leſſe for what you are Not, then for what you Are, to that diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Mercy of his, to which alone you owe your Exemption from miſeries, as great as the Bleſſings it conferrs on you:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.7.</note> For, <hi>Who maketh thee to differ?</hi> is a Queſtion, that may be as well askt in reference to our externall, as to our Spirituall Condition. Which invites me to mind you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that you are yet more engag'd to Gods Love, for Protecting you from thoſe groſſe Vices, that Disfigure moſt mens
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:48185:73"/>minds, than from thoſe leſſe Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, though more reſented, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that Diſtemper their Bodyes.</p>
            <p>For, Ambition, Luſt, Avarice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and ev'n that vain Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which young Gentlemen are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally pleaſ'd to think ſo Innocent, are really more Formidable and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſeaſes and Calamities, than thoſe that reduce men to take Phyſick, or thruſt them into Hoſpitalls. To e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the truth of which Paradox, I hope I ſhall not need to mind you of judging of the Dangerouſneſſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes by the Nobleneſſe of the part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, ſince I can tell you, that He that cannot erre, ſeems dayly to juſtifie our Aſſertion, by inflicting Sickneſſe and the ſharpeſt outward Calamities on his own Deareſt Children, to preſerve them from the Contagion of Sinne, or Cure them of the unfilial habitudes of it. And therefore, ſince, when we ſee a tender Mother apply a painfull Cauſtick to the neck of her Favorite-Infant, threatned by the Apoplexie; we ſcruple not to conclude that ſhe thinks the trouble of an Iſſue an Evill infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to Convulſion-fits. So when we
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:48185:74"/>ſee our Heavenly Father ſend Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Croſſes to reſcue thoſe he Loves from the Contagion or the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Sinne; we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, he thinks Affliction a leſſe Evill than Guilt, ſince he is too Wiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent a Phyſitian to Cure with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy worſe than the Diſeaſe. In the 8th of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> there is a Caution given the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> leaſt Proſperity (which is wont to be a kind of Lethe, that makes men Forget all, but their Enjoyments) ſhould make any of them ſay in his heart,
<note place="margin">Deut. 8.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>My power and the might of my hand hath gotten me this Wealth. But</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>they ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord their God: for it is he, that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them power to get wealth.</hi> It is not the revolting <hi>Iſraelites</hi> onely, of whoſe Ignorance of his Bounty God may complain as he did by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, by whom he ſaid, <hi>I taught Ephraim to go taking them by their armes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.3.</note> 
               <hi>but they knew not, that I healed them:</hi> and there are but too many, of whom he might ſay, as he did by the ſame Prophet; <hi>For ſhe did not know that I gave her Corn and Wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 1.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>and Oyle, and multiply'd her Silver, and her Gold, which they prepar'd
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:48185:74"/>for Baal: Therefore will I return and take away my Corn in the time thereof, and my Wine in the Seaſon thereof; and will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Wool and my Flax given to cover her Nakedneſſe.</hi> And this will make way for the Deſign I had to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Advantagiouſneſſe of Gods Love, by ſaying, That as for Spirituall Goods; he gives us in this life ſo rich an Earneſt of expected Joyes, that ev'n the Earneſt is a Stock large enough to ſubſiſt with Comfort on, and really out-values and tranſcends all thoſe Momentary Pleaſures, it requires us to forſake, to keep up a Title to Eternall ones. But to particularize God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to us in This very life, would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly take up a conſiderable part of it; And yet the Love, God bears us, dyes not with us, nor doth (as mens Affections) either endure a Funerall in our Tombs, or ſurvive onely in an uſeleſſe Grief (or an Eſteem as boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe:) No, Gods Love is ſo far from reſembling the uſuall ſort of friends, who, when they have accompanied us to the Grave, do There leave us; that, like the Angells, that <hi>carried Lazarus's Soul to Abrahams boſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note> its Officiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:48185:75"/>begins then moſt to Appear, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our dark eyes are Cloſ'd, and is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Trueſt to the beloved Soul, when ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Forſakes the Body, giving each bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saint cauſe to ſay of God, what <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi</hi> did of <hi>Boaz:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 2.20.</note> That, <hi>He hath not le<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> off his kindneſſe to the Living, and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dead.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Now,</hi> indeed (ſays our Saviour'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Favorite) <hi>are we the Sonns of God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but we know, when he ſhall appear, we ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be like him,</hi> This bleſt Expectance muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be now my Theme, becauſe the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Limits, which my Deſign hath plac't to this Diſcourſe, (of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages accruing from Gods Love) will leave no more room untaken up by Heaven.</p>
            <p>But,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>19</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> before I proceed to ſet forth to you the Greatneſſe of the Felicity reſerv'd for us in Heaven; It will, I fear, be requiſite to mind you of the Lawfullneſſe of having an Eye on it. For many not-undeſervedly applauded Preachers, have of late bin pleaſ'd to teach the people, that to Hope for Heaven is a Mercenary, Legal, and therefore Unfiliall Affection. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to hope for Heaven, as Wages
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:48185:75"/>for Work perform'd, or by way of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in the proper and ſtrict Acception of that tearm, were a Preſumption, to which none of the Divines, we diſſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom, can be too much an Enemie, nor perhaps more ſo, then I am. But to take in Gods Bleſſings among the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of Loving God, is but to do as he did, who ſaid, <hi>I love the Lord, becauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.1.</note> 
               <hi>he hath heard my voyce, and my Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and to look upon the Joyes of Heaven, to comfort and ſupport us in the hardſhips and loſſes, to be undergon in our Journey thitherward, is to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate no worſe a man than <hi>Moſes,</hi> of whom it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.26.</note> that <hi>he esteemed the reproach of Chriſt greater riches, than the Treaſures in Aegypt: for he had reſpect,</hi> or turned his Eye <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unto the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the reward.</hi> It is indeed, <hi>Linda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> a happy Frame of mind, to be able to love God purely for Himſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Glance at our own Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But though, I dare not deny, that it is poſſible to attain to ſo High and diſintereſs'd a kind of Love, yet I think, that that Excellency ſuppoſ'd to be Vouchſaf'd to ſome men, is not by the Scripture Exacted as a Duty
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:48185:76"/>from All men. Were all the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Piety of a worldly Nature and to be Here receiv'd, the Actions invited to, by the Intuition of it, might paſſe for Mercenary. But when Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is chiefly hoped for, as it will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us unto the Fruition of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Chriſt, and that the Other Joye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expected there are ſo farre from being of a Senſual or Worldly nature, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they are known not to be attainable till by Death the Senſes and Bodye themſelves and all the meerly Anima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Faculties be aboliſht; for a Heaven ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſider'd, I ſay, to forgo readily al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Pleaſures of the Senſes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo cheerfully all the Hardſhips and Dangers, that are wont to attend a Holy life, is, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> ſuch a kind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mercenarineſſe, as none, but a reſigned Noble, and believing Soul, is likely to be guilty of. If I ſhould ſay, that Fear it ſelf, and even the feare of Hell may be one Juſtifiable Motive of Mens Actions, though I ſhould propoſe, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe I am reaſoning with, would think a Paradox; yet I ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hold forth therein no more than the Scripture does,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:48185:76"/>fear,</hi> (ſaies the writer to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi>) <hi>leſt, a promiſe being left us of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into his rest, any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it.</hi> And no leſſe eminent a Herauld of the Goſpell, than St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſo ſucceſſefully maintain'd the Evangelicall againſt the Legall Spirit, thus profeſſeth of himſelf, <hi>I keep under my body, and bring it into Subjection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>leſt by any means, when I have preach'd to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi> And 'twas not to Slaves or Hirelings, that Chriſt directs this Admonition: <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> my Friends,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Be not afraid of them that kill the Body, and after that have no more that they can doe: But I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn you whom you ſhall fear, Fear him, which after he hath kill'd, hath power to caſt into Hell; Yea, I ſay unto you</hi> (a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, which the preſent Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie ſhews, not to have been Cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) <hi>Fear Him.</hi> Where the paraphraſe given of God, is not barely Deſcriptive but Ratiocinative (to borrow thoſe tearms of the Schools) informing us not only Who we ſhould, and ſhould not fear: but Why, we ſhould fear the one and not the other. As when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>I know whom I have truſted,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:48185:77"/>he means what manner of Perſon,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>how Faithfull</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> elſewhere calls God) <hi>and how Omnipotent:</hi> whence immediately he adds, <hi>And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>that he is able to keep that, which I have committed unto him againſt that day.</hi> More Texts of the ſame Import might be added, if the Deſign of thoſe already alledg'd were other, than to Facilitate the Admiſſion of the more Plauſible truths we have been make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and which to us ſeems very cleerly held forth in thoſe and the like Scriptures, which are therefore cited out of the new Teſtament, that they might have the greater authority with one ſort of our Antagoniſts.
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>I preſſe toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they, that do his Commandements that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in through the Gates into the City.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>Laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good Foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold of Eternall life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>To them who by patient Continuing in well-doing, ſeek for (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Glory and Honor, and Immortality, eternal Life.</hi> And of Chriſt himſelf, whoſe love to God
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:48185:77"/>is queſtionleſſe Filiall and unequal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, 'tis ſaid,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2</note> 
               <hi>looking unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the Joy that was ſet before him endured the Croſſe, deſpiſ'd the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi> Nor ſee I, why it ſhould be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filiall for a Child of God to further the Raiſing of thoſe Paſſions, which his Heavenly Father intends to have raiſ'd in him, upon the ſame Grounds and Motives, that God is pleaſ'd to imploy to Excite them. And ſince the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeems plainly to invite our Hopes by recording St. <hi>Pauls</hi> having ſaid,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Every man that ſtriveth for the maſtery is temperate in all things; now they do it to obtain a corruptible Crown, but we an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible:</hi> And by repreſenting our Saviour himſelf as ſaying in one place, <hi>Reioyce, and be exceeding glad;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5 12.</note> 
               <hi>for great is your reward in Heaven:</hi> In another, <hi>Be thou faithfull unto Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>and I will give thee a Crown of Life;</hi> And in divers others, ſpeaking to the like purpoſe: Since, I ſay, the Scripture ſeems thus to Allure our Hopes, Would it not be kind of accuſing it of an aptneſſe to delude and enſnare us, To teach that it propoſeth us the powerfulleſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:48185:78"/>to Incite our paſſions, if it be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to cheriſh and harbour the Paſſions naturally belonging to thoſe Objects. And certainly, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> ſince God, who as our Creatour knows the Frame and Conſtitution of mans Soul, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably better than he himſelfe; is pleas'd to deal with our Hopes and our Fears, to engage us to his Service: It very ill becomes Us, either to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with his Methods of working on our Spirits, or to reject any help, which he has been pleas'd to afford a piety, which, for ought ever I could obſerve, does ev'n in the Beſt men find reſiſtance enough to keep any Help that can be imploy'd to promote it from being Superfluous. And truely, the animating or diſcouraging In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, that Hope or the Want of it, is wont to have upon our Indeavours, makes me very apprehenſive, that ſince the enlivning hopes of Heaven are not able to make moſt mens Endeavours other than very Languid, the forbidding thoſe ſupporting hopes would ſoon weaken and decreaſe our Endeavours into none at all.</p>
            <p>But,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>20</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> though I may perhaps have taken ſome Pains in ſtudying
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:48185:78"/>Controverſiall Divinity, yet I take ſo little Pleaſure in writing of it, that though not only a Seaſonable Duty to truth, but a Neceſſary one to the enſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of this Diſcourſe, have preſſ'd me to ſerve in this cauſe; yet I ſhall perhaps obtain Your pardon ſooner than my own, for having thus long ſuſpended the diſcourſing to you of the <hi>Advantagiouſneſſe</hi> of Gods love to us, as it gives us Here a Right, and wil Hereafter givs us Admiſſion to Heaven. Heaven, the bright Seat of ſo much happineſs, that we ſhall ſcarcely count amongſt our Joyes, that Heaven is the Seat of them: There the Excellency of the poſſeſſed Goods, ſhall as much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint our Expectations, as in other fruitions, the Emptineſſe is wont to do. The Apoſtle tells us, That <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9</note> 
               <hi>neither have entred into the heart of Man, the things which God hath prepar'd for them that love Him.</hi> Such pure refin'd Delights, not onely ſtoop not unto Senſe, but are ſublime enough ev'n to tranſcend Imagination. When Fancy hath form'd and ſhap't the perfecteſt Ideas, that its abſtractions can make, of Bleſſedneſſe; our owne more happy Experiences of greater,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:48185:79"/>muſt diſabuſe us, when we come to Heaven, which is a Soyle, whoſe Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe is ſo confin'd to Joy, that ev'n our Diſappointments and miſtakes ſhal there contribute to our Happineſſe, which doth ſo much partake of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity, whoſe Gift it is, that you ſee the Apoſtle gives it a Negative De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: and to create in us Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, underogatory from what we ſhall poſſeſſe, not onely removes our thoughts from all we Do Enjoy, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts them above all that we Can Fancy. At which way of proceeding, that you may the leſſe wonder, <hi>Lindamor;</hi> be pleaſ'd to conſider, that in Heaven our Faculties ſhall not onely be Gratify'd with ſuitable and acceptable Objects, but ſhall be Heightn'd and Enlarg'd, and conſequently our Capacities of happineſſe, as well Encreaſ'd as Fill'd; A child not yet releaſ'd out of the homely Priſon of the Womb, cannot there poſſibly frame Ideas of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, which will be afforded him by the pleaſing Noiſes and the glittering Objects, that will preſent themſelves to him after his Birth. And the ſame Child whil'ſt he continues in his Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, though he may with delight look
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:48185:79"/>upon Emblems finely drawn and Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and may take ſome pleaſure in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the neat and ſurprizing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, and floriſhes of a Greek and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Bible, curiouſly Printed, yet he cannot then Imagine the Pleaſure, the ſame Objects will afford him, when Age and Study ſhall have ripen'd and inſtructed his Intellectualls, and made him capable both of Underſtanding, and Relliſhing the excellent Moralities, couch'd in thoſe ingenious Emblems, and the profound and ſaving Myſteries, wherewith that divine Book, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, eſpecially in its Originall Tongues, does to an Intelligent and religious Peruſer, appear repleniſht. Such a double advantage, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> among others, the Admiſſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven brings thoſe, to whom that bleſſing is vouchſaf'd: for, beſides that Set of Objects, (if I may ſo ſpeak) ſo New and ſo Peculiar to Heaven, that their Idea's could never enter into mens thoughts before their Admiſſion there; Beſides this, I ſay, our then enlarg'd Capacities will enable us ev'n in Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which were not altogether Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to us before, to diſcern things formerly Undiſcern'd, and derive
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:48185:80"/>thence both new and greater Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Delights. Wonder not, <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damor,</hi> that in mentioning the Joyes of Heaven, I uſe the Expreſsions I find leaſt Detractory from a Theme as much above our Praiſes, as the Heaven they are injoy'd in, is above our Heads. For, though ſuch Expreſsions may ſeem ſomewhat tumid and aſpiring; and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much for one, that Celebrates, then for one, that but Aſſerts: yet cannot I ſcruple, to uſe Seeming Hyperboles in the mention of Felicities, which make the higheſt Hyperboles but Seeming ones; For theſe joyes, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> are like the Stars of Heaven, which by reaſon of our Remoteneſſe from them appear extreamly Little, though really in themſelves they are ſo Vaſt, that a leſſe than the largeſt, is by Odd Greater then the biggeſt Object upon Earth, nay then the whole Earth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe. And therefore, as if I were to take you with me to contemplate th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Planets, I would ſhow you the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through ſuch a Teleſcope, as by great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe bright Objects in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what to the unasſiſted Eye the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appear, doth ſomewhat leſſen the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of Remoteneſſe, and ſhow
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:48185:80"/>them with leſſe Detraction from their true Magnitude; So mentioning to you the Felicities of Heaven, I think it not Unlawfull, or Improper, to endeavour by repreſentations, tranſcending what they Appear, to give you Notions leſſe inferiour to what they Are.</p>
            <p>In Heaven, then,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>21</label> we ſhall taſt Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe enough, to enable us to rectifie the Definition of it: We may there be inſtructed, how to Name and Rate all Goods by thoſe that will Concenter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Felicity we ſhall poſſeſſe; which ſhall be there made up of the Confluence, Perfection, and Perpetuity of all true Joyes; for, Heaven will make us happy, not (as Philoſophy pretends to do) by the Confinement, but by the Fruition of our Deſires: which ſhall neither Fail in the Choice of their Objects, nor Miſſe of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them; but be, both uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly Juſt, and infallibly Accompliſh't: In the former of which properties, (as our then Rectify'd reaſon wil conſider things) we ſhall think our ſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier (yet) than in the latter. We ſhall there Reſemble the Saints we here Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and ſhall not onely ſee and be like thoſe pious Worthies, whoſe vertues
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:48185:81"/>Eclipſe theirs, which among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Deify'd leſſe deſerving Heroes thoſe excellent Perſons that did as well Ennobles as Inſtruct Mankind, giving us cauſe to Glory, and to Bluſh that we are Men, and whoſe Stories have the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Honour of being recorded by Inſpired Pens; Thoſe <hi>Spirits,</hi> I ſay, <hi>of juſt men made perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> as the Scripture terms them, ſhall be our Conſtant and familiar Company, into whoſe bleſſed Society we ſhal not onely be Welcome, but Encreaſe it. In Heaven, we ſhall have a bleſt and familiar Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thoſe ſame glorious Spirits, whoſe Nature doth inveſt them with ſuch a Luſtre, that all the Diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Diſguizes, when they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to us, doth ſcarce ſuffice to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine our Raptures to Reſpects below Idolatry, and darken them into Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for our Wonder, not Adoration. There we ſhall ſee (a ſight worth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for) that Bleſſed Saviour, of whom the Scripture does ſo Much and ſo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently entertain us, and who having done and ſuffer'd ſo much for us, does ſo highly deſerve of us both upon the ſcore of his Infinite Perfections, and upon the account of his Ineſtimable
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:48185:81"/>Benefits. Yes, there ſhall we ſee that Holy and Divine Perſon, who when he vouchſaf'd (as his Favorite-Diſciple ſpeaks) to <hi>to pitch his Tent among us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Joh. 1.14.</note> and dwell with men on Earth, to fit them by his Merits and Example to dwell with him in Heaven, did ſo admirably mixe an awefull Majeſty with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Meekneſſe, and the aſſum'd Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of his humane Nature with the ſeaſonable Coruſcations of his Divine; expreſſing in his whole life, ſo Perfect and Exemplary a Vertue, and yet ſo much Sweetneſſe and Gentleneſſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe Aſpirers to it, that were the moſt Short of it, that the Jews them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could ſay of him, That <hi>he had done all things well;</hi> and his very Enemies, that were imploy'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him as a Malefactour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ'd to thoſe, that ſent them, That <hi>never man spake like him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 7.46.</note> And his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who had moſt Opportunity to Pry narrowly into his Actions, and were of a Condition and Breeding very unlike to infuſe into them Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Reſolutions, did, in Spight of the frequent Reproofs their failings extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him, and of the Hardſhips that attended his Service, think ev'n
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:48185:82"/>Death it ſelfe in his Company, more Elegible,
<note place="margin">Joh. 11.16</note> then Life led out of it; <hi>Let us alſo go that we may dye with him,</hi> (ſayes ev'n the diſtruſtfull <hi>Thomas,</hi> to his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Diſciples.) But, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> we ſhal there ſee the Son of God, not in that <hi>Form of a Servant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> which he put on that he might Suffer for us, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his Prieſtly and Prophetick Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions here below; but in that Regall State and Condition, which belongs to him by vertue of his Kingly office, on whoſe ſcore he is ſtyl'd in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">Rev. 19.16.</note> 
               <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> All power or authority being (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſpeaks) given Him both in Heaven and in Earth.
<note place="margin">Matth. 28 18.</note> And how Nobly atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded may we ſuppoſe this Divine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch to be in his Exalted Condition in Heaven, when in his ſtate of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation on Earth,
<note place="margin">Mar. 1.13</note> whilſt he was in the VVilderneſſe among the wild Beaſts, the Angells are recorded to have miniſtred unto him; and, whilſt he lay ſwath'd in a homely manger,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the Coeleſtial hoſt were heard to ſolemnize his miraculous Birth according to that paſſage of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>When he bringeth in the first begotten into the World (he ſaith)</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:48185:82"/>
               <hi>And let all the Angells of God worſhip him!</hi> And yet ſuch conſiderable and Noble Creatures, thoſe Immateriall Intelligences call'd Angells, are,
<note place="margin">2 King. 19.35.</note> that One of them in One night was able to deſtroy above a hundred and fourſcore thouſand men, in the blaſphemous <hi>Senacherib</hi>'s impious Camp. And ſo much Majeſty, and Superiority, does their Nature give them, in reference ev'n to the eminenteſt of Mortalls, That, when the undaunted <hi>Joſuah</hi> had boldly challeng'd one of them, that appear'd to him in the likeneſſe of a Man, and demanded, Whom he was for? when he knew him to be an Angel (unleſſe he ſuppoſ'd him to be that promiſ'd Meſſiah, who is elſewhere call'd <hi>the Angell of the Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.1.</note> as it is in the Originall, and in the ſame Text, <hi>the Lord</hi>) he alters his Addreſſe unto him into this Submiſſive one,
<note place="margin">Joſh. 52 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>What ſaith my Lord unto his Servant;</hi> and ev'n wiſe and holy <hi>Daniel</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who was the Second perſon of the World for Power, and the Firſt for much nobler Attributes, Wiſdom and Underſtanding, who ſaw ſo many Governours of vaſt Provinces, and Profeſſours of admired Magick, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:48185:83"/>to himſelf, yet confeſſes to the Angell, that appear'd to him, That he was confounded and diſanimated at his preſence, and addes, <hi>How can the Servant of this my Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>talk with this my Lord.</hi> We may ſafely therefore expect that we ſhall then behold our Saviour not in thoſe Diſguiſes, which disfigur'd him in their Eyes, that only conſider'd his Sufferings; but in that triumphant Condition, wherewith they are now Rewarded. The Thorns of his (now no more Galling, but Adorning) Crown will appear upon that radiant Head of His, more glorious, than thoſe of the flaming Buſh,
<note place="margin">Exod 3.2</note> wherein God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to <hi>Moſes.</hi> And we ſhall not ſee, that deſpicable forme, which made the Prophet ſay (perſonating the Generality of the Jewiſh Nation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with the Meſſias) — <hi>He hath no Form,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.2.</note> 
               <hi>nor Comelineſſe, and when we ſhall ſee him, there is no Beauty, that we ſhould deſire him.</hi> But we ſhall ſee him Encompaſſ'd with ſo much Majeſty, and Shining with ſo much of his genuine Splendour and Beauty, that we ſhall deſervedly eſteem him <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>the admirable.</hi> And our raviſht Souls ſhall by the more attentive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:48185:83"/>of him, but find more cauſe to imitate the Spouſe in <hi>Solomons</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick <hi>Epithalamium;</hi> who having dwelt upon the Beauty of the ſeverall parts, that concurr'd to the accompliſhing the divine Bridegroom, exclaims in an Epiphonema, very contrary to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion lately mention'd in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>He is altogether Deſires,</hi> or,
<note place="margin">Cant. 5.10.</note> by an Hebraiſm, <hi>Moſt deſirable,</hi> which our Engliſh renders, <hi>He is altogether love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> His eyes will there appear, as St.
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> repreſents them, of active Fire, and will into the willing Breaſts of the Raviſht beholders ſhoot Flames as Pure, as Holy, and as Deathleſſe, as thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church, who believ'd not the Angels altogether Incorporeall, may be ſuppos'd to have conceived the Seraphims to conſiſt of. Certainly, ſince (as the Scripture informs us) <hi>It never entred into the Heart of Man, what God has reſerv'd in Heaven for thoſe that love him;</hi> That Glory can be but Imperfectly expreſſ'd by the bare Epithet of Inconceivable, with which God rewards the meritorious Sufferings and Obedience of that Only begotten Son of his love; For whoſe ſake, he is pleas'd to confer on ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:48185:84"/>Thouſands of men, unimaginable Glories. He that vouchſafes ev'n to many of his Servants a brightneſſe like that of the Starrs,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> will ſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate a more radiant Luſtre to the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> that Only Son of His, <hi>whom</hi> (to borrow inſpir'd Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) <hi>he hath appoynted Heir of all things by whom alſo he made the worlds:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Who being the brightneſſe of his Glory, and the expreſſe Image of his perſon, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himſelf purg'd our Sinns, ſate down on the right hand of the Majesty on high, farre above all Principality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.21</note> 
               <hi>and Power, and Might, and Dominion, and every Name, that is named not only in this World, but in that which is to come,</hi> Thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting him not onely above all Earthly Princes and Potentates, but ev'n above the Higheſt Orders of the Spirits of the Coeleſtial Hierarchie.</p>
            <p>But apprehend not,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>22</label>
               <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that this ſublime Exaltation of Chriſt will make him Deſpiſe the meaneſt of his Saints, or diſdain communion with him; For, St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, That he was in the <hi>form of God,</hi> when he vouchſaf'd to take upon him the form of a Servant, to make us Free; and, ſure,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:48185:84"/>he that condeſcended ſo far, and ſtoop'd ſo low, to Invite and Bring us to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, will not refuſe us a gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception there. In the dayes of his fleſh he was pleas'd to own <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ev'n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Diſhonours of the Grave, and vouchſaf'd him in that deſpicable Condition the Glorious Title of his Friend. And when he deſcended the Mount of Olives, all the loud Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the glad Multitude, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ung <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> to him, and ſtrow'd his way with their Palms,
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.37, 38—41</note> their Veſtments and their Praiſes, could not divert him from Deploring, ev'n with Teares, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem's</hi> approaching Fate; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing in the midſt of his Triumphs a Concern, for the very worſt and ſtubborneſt of his Enemies. And, leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhould be thought, that he was thus concern'd for worthleſſe Mortalls, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y whilſt he ſhar'd and felt the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies of their Condition; Give me leave to obſerve to you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmediately after his Reſurrection whilſt the Senſe of the ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exampl'd Change of his Condition was Freſh upon him, and the Remembrance of the Apoſtles Ingratitude in deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, almoſt as Recent; he ſticks not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:48185:85"/>to give thoſe very Diſciples that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him, the glorious Title, and that a more familiar one then we find him to have allow'd them on Earth, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his Brethren;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.10.</note> and particularly ſhows himſelf Sollicitous for that <hi>Peter,</hi> who, in ſpight of all thoſe empty Boaſts,
<note place="margin">Mar. 16.7</note> wherewith he not only ſeem'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Death, but Chriſts Prediction too, did not onely Forſake his Maſter, but Deni'd him. He can in Heaven be ſo concern'd for his diſtreſſ'd members here on earth, that not onely he can take Notice of expiring <hi>Stephen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that cloud of fatall Stones, that batter'd down his Priſon; and can, when <hi>Saul</hi> was perſecuting the vulgar Chriſtians, cry out unto him, <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>why perſecuteſt thou Me?</hi> as if He, and thoſe, that Love him, were but One: But in the meſſages,
<note place="margin">In the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> chapters of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalyps.</hi>
               </note> he ſends to the Angels or Governours of the ſeven Churches, he ſufficiently manifeſts, That ſingle Chriſtians may be as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in his thoughts, as if they had no other Object: His Greatneſſe will not make his Kindneſſe leſſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, but only more Obligeing; He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains not ev'n after his Aſcenſion to ſay; <hi>Behold; I ſtand at the door and knock,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:48185:85"/>if any man hear my voyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.20</note> 
               <hi>and open the door, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> That King, in the Parable, by whom Himſelfe is repreſented,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> is pleas'd himſelf to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come each Individual truſty Servant with a peculiar, <hi>Euge bone Serve;</hi> And in another Parable he ſcruples not, to repreſent the great Condeſcenſions and Familiarity, wherewith the Lord ſhall remunerate the faithfull and watchfull Servants, by telling his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe Servants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.37.</note> 
               <hi>whom the Lord, when he commeth, ſhall find ſo watching. Verily, I ſay unto you, that he ſhall gird himſelf, and will make them to ſit down to meat, and will come forth to ſerve them.</hi> At which Expreſſion, you will the leſſe Admire, if you Conſider, that beſides that it is Parabolicall, and probably Hyperbolicall, and therefore not to be taken (as the French ſpeak, <hi>au pied de la lettre</hi>) in a ſtrict ſenſe: We find in the Evangelicall Story that our Saviour diſdain'd not to converſe familiarly with Publicans and Sinners, nor ev'n to Waſh the Feet of his own Diſciples. And ſince he condeſcended to ſuch
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:48185:86"/>familiarity to thoſe frail Mortalls, ſo many of whom were apt to turne the Favours of God into Want onneſſe, we may the leſſe admire his gracious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſions to thoſe, the Sinleſſeneſſe of whoſe Condition will keep them from turning his Vouchſafements into any thing, but Occaſions of Joy and Gratitude. Marvaile not, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> as at an Impertinencie, that I appear ſo Sollicitous to poſſeſſe you with high Apprehenſions of the ſuper-eminent Dignity and Felicity of our exalted Saviour; And, that in the Loftieſt and moſt magnificent Expreſſions, the Scripture affords me, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make out to you, that the bright Sun of Righteouſneſſe is now grown uncapable of ſuffering Eclipſes, but ſhines with unclouded and une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall'd Splendour, and that we ſhall in Heaven (as the Writer to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>ſee Jeſus who was made a a little</hi> (or for a ſhort while,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>lower than the Angells, for the ſuffering of Death, crown'd with Glory and Honour.</hi> For it will make Heaven more Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us, to find Him raigning there,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:48185:86"/>who hath Suffer'd ſo much for us; and for whom, if we e're come thither, we ſhall have ſo much Suffer'd. For, ſince our Love will, as the reſt of our ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Graces, be perfected, and grow Compleat in Heaven; The ineffable Happineſſe of our Dear Redeemer, muſt needs bring an Encreaſe to ours, commenſurate to the Ardency of our Love for him, and we ſhall reliſh no Happineſſe more than That; which is therefore Ours, becauſe He is happy, and Suppoſes in Him, what it Conferrs on Us. Beſides that, ſince the Regall Dignity, wherein (as Mediator) he is Inſtated, may make us owe our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Sentence, as well as to his Merits; Heaven it ſelf will be ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly endear'd to us, by our Injoying it upon his Account. I need not tell you, what a value Lovers are wont to ſet upon the leaſt Favours, that can be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them by their Miſtreſſes, and that oftentimes a worthleſſe Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a Bracelet of Hair, or ſome ſuch Trifle that nothing can make precious but Hir preſenting it, is highlyer va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by the tranſported Lover, than
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:48185:87"/>the richeſt Preſents of Nature, or of Fortune. How great a Bleſſing muſt it then be, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> to owe Joyes, that need no endearing Circumſtances to merit the name of Happineſſe, to a Perſon ſo belov'd, that even Heaven it ſelf will bring more Felicity to the amorous Soul, as it is a Proof of his Love, than as it is a Donative of his Bounty: As paſſionate Brides do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably more value the Wedding-Rings, which their glad Lovers give them, as Pledges, than as Gold. 'Tis ſaid of the perſecuted and diſgrac'd Apoſtles, that <hi>they rejoyced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o have been counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.41.</note> But if they deſervedly Rejoyced, to be allow'd to Suffer for him; of how much Joy ſhall they have juſt cauſe, that are admitted to Reign with him. His having ſupported the Hardſhips and the Toyles (for I muſt not now call them Evills) to which our afflicted Condition of Mortality is Expos'd, does ſo much alleviate them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh us under them, that in this ſenſe alſo it may be truly ſaid,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> That <hi>the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:48185:87"/>by his hurts we are healed.</hi> But he that Reliev'd us even by his Croſſe, will ſure do more for us by his Crown; when he ſhal Admit, and even Invite, each faithfull Servant to no leſſe a Bleſſing, than,
<note place="margin">Matt. 25.21.</note> 
               <hi>to enter into his Maſters joy.</hi> So rich a Source of Happineſſe did Chriſt deſigne, to make himſelf to us in all his Capacities and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that in Heaven and in Earth, it Was, and Will be, his gracious and conſtant Imployment, to Share our Griefs, or Impart to us his Joyes; and either Leſſen our Miſeries by his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, or Encreaſe our Happineſſe by his Felicity.</p>
            <p>Expect not, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>23</label> that I ſhould Solemnly beg your Pardon, for this ſeeming Excurſion, till I come to think it a Digreſſion, to inſiſt on the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of Chriſt in Heaven, treating of the Happineſſe, which thoſe that Love him will enjoy there. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, not to ſpend time in imploring a needleſſe Forgiveneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I ſhall proceed to tell you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that in Heaven, we ſhall not onely ſee our Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt, but probably alſo all our
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:48185:88"/>Kindred, Friends, and Relations, that Living here in his Fear, Died in his Favour. For, ſince onr Saviour tells us,
<note place="margin">Luk. 20.36.</note> that <hi>the Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>equall to,</hi> or like, <hi>the Angels;</hi> who yet in the Viſions of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> appear to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with each other; Since in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the miſerable Epicure, and the happy Beggar,
<note place="margin">Luk 16.</note> the Father of the Faithfull is repreſented, as knowing, not onely the Perſon, and preſent Condition, but the paſt Story of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus.</hi> Since the Inſtructor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, confidently expects his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Pious <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> to be <hi>his Crown</hi> at <hi>that Great Day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.19, 20.</note> When the <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving turned many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſhall, as the Scripture foretells,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12 3.</note> confer a Star-like and Immortall Brightneſſe. Since (which is chiefly conſiderable) the Knowledge of particular Actions, and, conſequently, Perſons, ſeems re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the attainment of that Great End of God, in the Day of Judgment; the Manifeſtation of his Punitive and Remunerative Juſtice: Since, I ſay, theſe Arguments, beſides divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:48185:88"/>are afforded us by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we may ſafely conclude it Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that we ſhall Know each other in a Place, where, ſince nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to Happineſſe can be wanting, we may well ſuppoe, (at leaſt, if we can Imagine Here, what we ſhall think There) that we ſhall not want ſo great a Satisfaction, as that of being knowingly Happy, in our Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, our Friends. Nor is this onely Probable, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> but 'tis not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, that thoſe friends that Know us in Heaven, ſhall Welcome us thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For, ſince Chriſt aſſures us, that the very Angels (though they be ſo far from being Related to our Perſons, that they are Forrainers to our very Nature) receive acceſſion of Joy for a relenting Sinner,
<note place="margin">Luk. 15.7.</note> that by Repentance Begins to turn towards God; You will not think it Abſurd, that in a Place, where Charity ſhall not onely conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, (as <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſpeaks) but grow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.8.</note> Our dear Friends ſhould rejoyce to ſee us, not onely Being to Turn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, but Come home to him. Nor is it unlikely, that our tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:48185:89"/>Souls ſhall mutually Congratulate each other, their having now fully eſcaped the numerous Rocks, and Shelves, and Quickſands, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Storms, and no leſſe dangerous Calms, through which they are at length arrived at that Peacefull Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where Innocence and Delight (which are here ſo ſeldom Matcht) are inſeparable Companions, both of each other, and each bleſſed Reſident. With thoſe friends we here Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we ſhall there Rejoyce. And 'twill be but need, that the Diſcovery of each other's Vertues, ſhould bring us to a mutuall Knowledge of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for otherwiſe, we ſhall be ſo Chang'd, that we ſhould never know our Friends (and ſhould ſcarce know our Selves, were not an eminent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Knowledge a part of that happy Change) For thoſe departed-Friends, whom, at our laſt Separation, we ſaw disfigured by all the ghaſtly Horrours of Death, we ſhall then ſee aſſiſting about the Majeſtick Throne of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21</note> with their once vile bodies transfigured into the likeneſſe of his
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:48185:89"/>glorious body, mingling their glad Acclamations with the Hallelujah's of Thrones, Principalities, and Powers, and the moſt dignifi'd Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of the Coeleſtiall Court. I need not tell you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that we ſhall be more juſtly Tranſported at this Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, than was good old <hi>Jacob</hi> at that of his ſon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom having long mourn'd for dead and loſt, he found not onely alive, but a great Favourite, ready to welcome him to an unknown Court: For, whereas the Patriarch ſaid to his ſon, <hi>Now let me dye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 46.30.</note> 
               <hi>ſince I have ſeen thy face;</hi> The ſeeing of our Friends in Heaven will aſſure us, that we ſhall for ever Live with them there. The Re-union of Friends being there as priviledg'd from Divorce, as that of Soul and Body, (which ſcarce will be more Strict and Satisfactory) For, here indeed, if our Friends do not allay our Love or Affection by unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Actions, or their contagious Sufferings, we commonly dote on them to a Degree, that, as it were, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces God to deprive us early of them, and Snatch our Idols, and his Rivalls,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:48185:90"/>from us. But there, our, on both ſides, compleated-Graces, will not onely Deſerve, but Allow a higher Strain of Friendſhip. The near Contemplation and Fruition of the infinitely tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Perfections of the Creator, keeping all our Kindneſſe to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, not onely Subordinate To the Love we owe to God, but Grounded On it; as Excited Needles, when they ſtick faſteſt to each other, owe their Union to their having both been tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by the Load-ſtone; to which they have therefore both of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably ſtronger Inclinations, than either to the other.</p>
            <p>There,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>24</label> we ſhall ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily underſtand thoſe Deep &amp; Obſcure Myſteries of Religion, which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt Clarks that love not to Flatter themſelves, acknowledge, they are unable fully to Comprehend; being, after all the Toyle and Induſtry of their anxious Enquiries, reduc'd to ſit down with the Apoſtle's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that depth, whoſe Bottom they cannot Fathom: there we ſhall Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:48185:90"/>thoſe obſcure paſſages of (That Divine book uncapable of flattery) The Scripture, which, for all that Bold Criticks and Learn'd Expoſitors have Attempted to Illuſtrate it, does ſtill continue obſcure. There, diſcerning how exquiſitly the ſeverall Parts of Scripture are fitted to the ſeverall Times, Perſons, and Occurrences, wherein their all-foreſeeing Author intended moſt to uſe them, we ſhall diſcern not onely a Reconcileableneſſe, but a Friendſhip, and perfect Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny betwixt thoſe Texts, that here ſeem moſt at Variance, and ſhal diſcover not onely the Senſe of the obſcurer paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but the Requiſitneſſe of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been written ſo obſcurely. That ſtrange and peculiar, as well, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Crypticall Method and Style of Scripture, which often coſts us ſo much Study to find it Rationall, we ſhall there diſcover to be Admirable, and worthy of its Omniſcient Author. There, I hope, we ſhall have clearly expounded to us thoſe Ridles of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which have, but too often, Tempted ev'n good men, to queſtion
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:48185:91"/>Gods Conduct in the Government of the World; whil'ſt the Calamities and Perſecutions of Vertue, and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence ſeem Approv'd by him, who Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulates Proſperities on their Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall Oppoſers. There, we ſhall be convinc'd, that all theſe Seeming Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities, which the Heathen thought fit to impute to the giddy Whimſies of a Blind femall Deity, are not onely Conſiſtent with Gods Juſtice and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but are Productions of it. And though ſuch a Beliefe do here to Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Perſons, ſeem perhaps a greater piece of Self-deniall, then to refraine from Wine, or Gold, or Miſtreſſes; yet in Heaven it will appear as Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as here we find it Difficult. For, as <hi>Bildad</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>We are but of yeſterday, and know nothing, becauſe our dayes upon Earth, are but a Shadow.</hi> And the Shortneſſe of our Tranſitory lives, not permitting us to Continue long enough Spectatours here, to ſee above a Scene or two at moſt of that great Play, acted by Mankind upon the Stage of the World, 'tis no wonder, we are apt to harbour ſiniſter thoughts of the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:48185:91"/>Contriver of a Plot, whoſe neither Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning nor End we are acquainted with: which is no leſſe injurious, than t'were to Cenſure the lofty Tragedian <hi>Seneca,</hi> or ſome other matchleſſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, having peruſed but a Piece of ſome Tragedy, whereof the Latter part never arrived at our view. But, when once Gods whole Plot (if I may ſo ſpeak) and Conduct in the Adminiſtration of the World, ſhall come to be Diſcloſ'd; all thoſe Revolutions and Occurrences of Empires, States, Families, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, which men are here ſo prone to Quarrell with, will there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo Juſt, ſo Requiſite, and ſo Seaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that thoſe very things, which Here tempted us to Deny God, ſhall There engage us to Praiſe him; and we ſhall not ſo properly be Satisfy'd with his Providence, as Raviſh't. But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, we ſhall be Tranſported with Wonder and Gratitude, when God ſhal vouchſafe to diſcover to his particular Servants, the Reaſons of his Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards them, and make out to them not onely the Neceſſity and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but ev'n Mercifulneſſe of thoſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:48185:92"/>very Afflictions, that were moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Severity, (no Stroke from Gods Paternall Hand, either lighting Sooner or falling Heavier, or ſtaying Longer, than the occaſion, that Extorted it, exacted) and convince them, that their Hopes were never Diſappointed, but to Secure their Title to Better things, than thoſe they hoped for; nor their Inferiour Intereſts prejudic'd, but for the advantage of their Supream ones. Yes, all that unwelcome Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that here ſurrounded our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind Underſtandings, will vaniſh at the dawning of that bright, and (as St.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> expreſſion may be interpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) eternall day, wherein the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of all thoſe Difficulties,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which here Exerciſ'd (and perhaps Diſtreſſ'd) our Faith, ſhall be granted us to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it. And I muſt profeſſe to you, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> (as Unfaſhionable as ſuch a Profeſſion may ſeem in a Gentleman not yet two and Twenty) that I find the ſtudy of thoſe excellent Themes, Gods Word, and his Providence, ſo Difficult, and yet ſo Pleaſing and Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that could Heaven afford me
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:48185:92"/>no greater Bleſſing than a clear Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the abſtruſe Miſteryes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Providence, I ſhould value the having my Underſtanding Gratifi'd and Enrich'd with Truths of ſo Noble and precious a Nature, enough to Court Heaven at the rate of renounce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it all thoſe unmanly Senſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and trifling Vanities, for which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Mortalls are wont to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite the Intereſt, their Saviour ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought them in it.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall we onely converſe with Saints and Angells,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>25</label> but with that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more glorious Deity, that made them, what they are, without at all Impoveriſhing Himſelfe. In Heaven, we ſhall enjoy (its Maker) God,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2. 1 Cor. 15.28.</note> and <hi>ſee Him as he is,</hi> who (as the Scripture tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us) ſhall then be <hi>all in all:</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing all the goods, we value in the Creatures, as eminently and fully, as the Sun doth the Light, that Twinkleth in the Starrs.</p>
            <p>If one,
<note place="margin">Anaxage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</note> that was none of the leaſt of the Philoſophers, ſcrupl'd not to tell the man that ask'd him, What he was borne for, that, It was to contemplate
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:48185:93"/>the Sun; If our beſt Naturaliſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though the darkneſſe that is here caſt upon things, and the dimneſſe of our Intellectual Eyes, (which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Aristotle</hi> fitly compares to thoſe of an Owle) permit us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern but very little of that Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſſe, which he has expreſſed in the Creation, are yet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tranſporeed and raviſh'd with a juſt Admiration of the Perfections, He has diſplayed in his Workman-ſhip. If the wiſe Queen that came ſo far to viſit <hi>Solomon,</hi> was put almoſt into an Extaſie, by the ſight of his, though Wiſe, yet Human, Ordering of things; And if the <hi>Angels themſelves</hi> (as <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> informs us) <hi>deſire to look into the myſterious contrivances of God,</hi> in order to Man's Redemption: How great a Satisfaction, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> may we juſtly conceive it muſt needs be, to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to See ſo much of God, as Heaven will Diſcover to us? Eſpecially, ſince ſo much of our future Happineſſe will conſiſt in that Beatifick Viſion, (as the School-men juſtly call it) that <hi>St. John</hi> concluded, that <hi>we ſhall be like God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:48185:93"/>we <hi>ſhal ſee Him as He is.</hi> And our Saviour himſelf paraphraſes our Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall felicity by this bleſſed Viſion,
<note place="margin">Matt. 5.8.</note> where he ſays, <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God:</hi> As on the other ſide the Writer to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> imployes the being deny'd the ſight of that Divine Object, as a Deſcription of extreme wretchedneſſe, in that Text, where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exhorted thoſe to whom he writes to <hi>follow peace and holineſſe;</hi> he adds,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> as the formidableſt Menace which he could make uſeof to Deterr them from ſleighting his Exhortation, <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> And by this Viſion our Saviour ſeems to deſcribe the happineſſe even of Angels; where, forbidding the Scandalizing of any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe little ones that beleeve in him, he adds, to enforce what he had ſaid, that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Angells do alwaies ſee the face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his Father in Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 18.10.</note> We ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo taken up with the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lation and Fruition of that Glorious Object, (in whoſe Infinity all goods are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncluded and Dilated) that Ages num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erleſſe as the Joyes That Beatifick Viſion abounds with, will ſcarce af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:48185:94"/>us leaſure for a Diverſion to any other Pleaſures, than thoſe it ſelf cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates; which are ſo Numerous, and ſo Entire, that we ſhall there Deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that we Have not, except more Tongues to ſing more Praiſes to him, or at leaſt a Capacity to pay him grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Thankss, for what we Have; And even thoſe Deſires, Gods gracious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation wil make, in being Conceiv'd, Accompliſhed: for, otherwiſe Heaven's Reſidents ſcarce know any other Want, then that of Need to Wiſh; The Compleat Bleſſedneſſe of their Condition, reducing them to a happy Uſeleſneſſe of Wiſhes, by affording them a full Prae-poſſeſſion of all the Objects of Deſire. There Time, like Fire, having deſtroy'd What ever it could prey on, ſhall at laſt Dye it ſelf, and ſhall Goe Out into Eternity. Whoſe Nature is ſuch, that though our Joyes, after ſome Centuryes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Years, may ſeem to have been grow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Elder, by having been enjoyed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages, yet will they really ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue New, not onely upon the ſcore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Welcomeneſſe and Freſhneſſe,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:48185:94"/>but by their perpetually Equall (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Infinite) Diſtance from a Period. There, our felicity ſhall alwaies be the Same, yet ever New. Wearineſſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing Imperfection, either in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or the Appetite; the Former of which is Impoſſible in God, and the Latter ſhall Ceaſe in Heaven; Where our Felicity ſhall be ſo Great, that Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety (it ſelf) ſhall not be needed as a part of it. And if Heaven do admit Variety, it may be ſuppoſed ſuch a one, as ſhall conſiſt in a Further Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Firſt Object (God), not a forſaking of it; and ſuch as ariſes from the fixt Beholding of the changing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necks of Doves, or ſuch as we may ſee in the diverſiſi'd Refractions of the ſame ſparkling Diamond. In God, there is ſuch a various Identity, that the Fruition of Him both Satisfies and Creates Deſires: though That, without Satiety; and This, without Diſquiet. Other Delights, like the uſuall Cloaths we wear, quickly grow Stale, and are ſoon Worn out; where as Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtiall Pleaſures participate the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the Jews Garments in the
<note place="margin">Deut 29.5</note>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:48185:95"/>Wilderneſſe, of not Impairing by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed Long. But as the amorous Needle, once joyn'd unto the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, would never, uncompell'd, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the inchanting Minerall; but, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages, cling no leſſe cloſely to it than at the firſt moment of their Union: So do the Saints in Heaven, with the ſame undiminiſht Freſhneſſe, ever poſſeſſe their Joyes, as if each mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were the Firſt that they poſſeſt them in. And if their Happineſſe do not improve by laſtinger Enjoyment, 'tis perhaps but becauſe it was at firſt uncapable of Increaſe. Or, if our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures do admit Acceſſion, they ſhall receive it from our Aſſurance, that we ſhall taſte them Ever, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually repeat (or rather continue) the ſame renewed Fruitions to an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, endear'd by nothing more, than by the quiet leiſure it will afford us, undiſtractedly to employ it, in Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating of the Author's Praiſes; and in a Condition, happier in that by it we grow paſt Doing, than paſt Suffering Ill. In Heaven, (in a word) our inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted Joyes will be ſo numberleſſe,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:48185:95"/>and ſo immenſe, that we ſhall need (as well as have) Eternity it ſelf to taſte them fully.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Lindamor,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>26</label> it was not my Deſign to give you a particular Topographie of this Coeleſtiall <hi>Canaan;</hi> but onely in a few words to let you ſee, that <hi>'tis, a Land flowing with Milk and Hony,</hi> And though I acknowledge, I have given you but dark Deſcriptions (and ſometimes, rather Poeticall than Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rographicall) of what the Apoſtle ſtyles,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>the Inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> Yet ſince, to whet our Longings for Fruitive (or Experimentall) Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg it is reſerv'd among the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of being in Heaven, to know how happy we ſhall be, when There: And ſince what the Scripture hath reveal'd of Paradiſe, ſeemes meant rather to Quicken our Obedience, then Satisfie our Curioſity; I may for thoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, have perhaps tolerably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd that taſke (of Heavenly Topo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie) by the acknowledgments of my Diſability to do it worthily. I ſhall now onely adde this Property of our expected Bliſſe, that the vaſt Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:48185:96"/>of Partners does detract no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from each private Share, nor does the Publickneſſe of it leſſen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in it. This Ocean of Felicity being ſo Shoarleſſe and ſo Bottomleſs, that all the Saints and Angels cannot exhauſt it, it being as impoſſible for any Aggregate of Finites to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend or exhauſt one Infinite, as 'tis for the greateſt number of Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Points to amount to, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, a Body. Our neighbour-regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe all enjoy the benefit of light as well as we; yet we enjoy not Leſſe, than if they enjoy'd None. Indeed, there is this difference between the Sun of Righteouſneſſe, and that of Heaven; that, whereas the later by his preſence Eclipſes all the Planets (his Attendants); the former, though radiant with a much mightier Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, will by his Preſence Impart it to his Saints: according to that of the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">Coll. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>When Chriſt who is our Life ſhall appear, then ſhall we alſo appear with him in Glory.</hi> So that the Elect, in relation to this Sun, ſhall not be like Starres, which his ſhining obſcures
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:48185:96"/>and makes to diſappear; but like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht Silver, or well glaz'd Armes, or thoſe vaſter Balls of burniſht Braſſe, the topps of Churches are ſometimes adorn'd with, which ſhine not till they be ſhin'd upon, and derive their glittering Brightneſſe and all the fire, that environs and illuſtrates them from their being expoſ'd (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkreen'd) to the Sun's refulgent beams.
<note place="margin">Cant. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>I am my beloved's, and my beloved is mine,</hi> ſayes every Saint (with the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) to hir Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. <hi>David</hi> ſayes of them that put their truſt in God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note> 
               <hi>That he ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſatisfie them with the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of His houſe, and make them drink of the River of his pleaſures:</hi> As if he meant to inſinuate, that, as when a multitude of perſons drink of the ſame River, none of them is able to exhauſt it, and yet each of them may have the full liberty of drinking as much as he can, or as much as he could though none but himſelfe ſhould be Allow'd to drinke of it: ſo whoſoever enjoyes God, enjoyes him wholly, or at leaſt doth enjoy him ſo
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:48185:97"/>entirely, in Relation to that man's ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity that the Fruition of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſts unenjoy'd of God, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Immenſity of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and not the Praepoſſeſſion of his Rivalls. The Angels, though of a Nature Differing from our's, and thereby plac'd above the perſonal Experience of our ſufferings, and infirmities, doe yet ſo ſympathize with us, that (as our Saviour informs us) they rejoyce at the repentance of a ſinner.</p>
            <p>And though, the members of the Church Militant, and thoſe of the Triumphant, live as farre aſunder, as Heaven is from Earth, and are not more Diſtant as to place, than Differing as to Condition; yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons all the Saints to be but <hi>one Family in Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3.15.</note> If then the diſparity of Reſidences, of Qualities, and of Conditions, cannot Now hinder the Lovers of God, from being ſo concern'd in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; how much of endearing Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may we ſuppoſe, that they will Enterchange, When both their Love
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:48185:97"/>ſhall be perfected, and all thoſe other Graces, that are proper to cheriſh and encreaſe it: For, the ſame Apoſtle, who, to aſſiſt us to conceive the ſtrictneſſe of the Union both betwixt Chriſt and his Saints, and the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, tells us, that <hi>He is the Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> and they <hi>are his Body, and Members, in particular;</hi> teaches us to make this inference That, (to expreſſe his Doctrine in his own words) <hi>If one Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffer all the Members ſuffer with it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>and if one Member be hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our'd, all the Members rejoyce with it.</hi> Yes, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> in that bleſt Condition, our wills being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly conform'd unto our Maker's, no Saint nor Angel can enjoy his Love without poſſeſſing a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate Degree of ours. And then, ſince perfect Friendſhip appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priates to each Friend the Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Proſperities of the other (as good <hi>Barzillai</hi> could not be highlier oblig'd by <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.37.</note> than
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:48185:98"/>by the Kings kindneſſe to his Son) each ſeverall Beatitude in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhall (in ſome ſort concern the whole Society, and) be Ours. As the Earth receives Addition of Light by the Sun's Beames beſtow'd upon the Starrs, and from the Moon refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon Her. And becauſe our perſonall Capacities are too too narrow, to contain all that Joy, we are (by the ſtrange Arithmetick of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) multiplyed into as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Happy Perſons, as there are Saints and Angells bleſt in Heaven. Our perfect Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Our Common Head, and mutuall Communion with each other, applying and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home every Felicity of theirs to us. This Friendly and reciprocall Sympathy, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching us each Glorified Saint's Bleſſedneſſe, and Him ours, by a bleſt Circulation, which makes us encreaſe, by our
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:48185:98"/>reſenting them, thoſe Joyes (of others) whoſe Encreaſe we reſent. But my Thoughts are ingaged in ſo good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>Lindamor,</hi> that they keep me from conſidering, how faſt the Hours paſſe, and have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt made me forget, that the Time which my Occaſions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me for Scribling to you, is ſo far ſpent, that not now at laſt to Reprieve you from the Perſecutions of my blunt Pen, were to be almoſt as Injurious to my own Affairs, as to your Patience. Hereafter yet, I may poſſibly make you ſome amends for this, with Riper Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Nature and Duties, or (if you will) the Properties and Returns of this Love, to which I have hitherto preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you ſome Motives. To (the laſt of) which, I might add; That, our Love to the Creature is an Earneſt, but to God 'tis
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:48185:99"/>a Title; the One makes Us the Object's, but the Other makes the Object Ours: That, ſince there is in Love ſo ſtrong a Magick, as to Transform the Lover in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Object Lov'd; We ought to be extreamly carefull of the Dedication of a Paſſion, which, as it is plac'd, muſt either Dignifie our Nature, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade it. And not to Addreſſe to any Lower (or, which is all one, to any Other) Object, the higheſt Intenſity of a Love, which cannot Stoop without our Degradation. And theſe I might Exſpatiate on, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit them with many other Motives, additionall to thoſe already inſiſted on; but that I may more properly reſerve them to the Treatiſe of the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that Love, whoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo partakes That of its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that there can hardly be produc'd more powerfull Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:48185:99"/>to it than the Conditions of it. Since then (as I freſhly intimated) I cannot but feare that your tir'd Patience, as well as my urgent Occaſions (though theſe will recall me to morrow Morning to my own VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne Hermitage) doth at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſummon me to leave you: and ſince I cannot do ſo in a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier place, than Heaven, I ſhall ſuſpend my Farewells, onely to begge you to believe, that ſo Noble a Motive of Exalting-Friendſhip, as the Ambition of rendring mine a fit Return for yours, hath ſo Improv'd my Kindneſſe that my Affection with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wronging its own Greatneſſe, could not Expreſſe it ſelf by any Leſſe Attempt, then this of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you the Greateſt and the moſt Deſireable of all Goods, by eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (that Noble Harbinger of your Soul,) your Love to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Whoſe Joyes alone are not
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:48185:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>Inferiour to thoſe which the Being made Inſtrumentall to procure them you, would really Create in,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR, Your moſt Faithfull, moſt Affectionate, and moſt Humble Servant,</hi> ROBERT BOYLE.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Leeſe</hi> 
                  <date>this 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48185:100"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
